<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;शतपथ-ब्राह्मणम् on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;शतपथ-ब्राह्मणम् on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>&#43;पाठ-भेदाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/pATha-bhedAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/pATha-bhedAH/</guid>
      <description>स्वरव्यत्यासः  स्वरव्यत्यास आकरेषु भिद्यन्ते। क्वचिद् एकतरो॑ वरो॑, ऽपरत्रा॑परः। य॑था  &amp;ldquo;व्रतमु᳘पैष्यन्&amp;rdquo; इति weber-मूले । किन्तु, &amp;ldquo;व्रत᳘मुपैष्यन्&amp;rdquo; इति वंशीधरशास्त्रि-मूले।  अ॒स्य वा॒क्य॑स्य विष॒ये तु वं॑शीधरशा॒स्त्रिणां॑ ग्रा॒ह्यः॑। व्रतॖमुपैष्यन्नॖन्तरेणाहवनीॖयञ्च गाॖर्हपत्यञ्च प्राङ् तिॖष्ठन् &amp;hellip; =व्र॒तमु॑पै॒ष्यन्नन्त॑रेणाहव॒नीयं॑ च॒ गार्ह॑पत्यं च॒ प्राङ्तिष्ठ॑न्। इ꣡त्य् उज्ज्वलः꣡ &amp;hellip;   &amp;ldquo;त᳘स्य भीत᳘स्य स्वो᳘ महिमा᳘पचक्राम&amp;rdquo; इति वॆबर-मूले । कि॑न्तु, &amp;ldquo;त᳘स्य भीतस्य स्वो᳘ महिमा᳘पचक्राम&amp;rdquo; इति वंशीधरशास्त्रि-मूले । अत्रैक॑म् उदा॒हर॑णं॒ यत्र॑ Weber-पा॒ठः सा॒धुर्वं॑शीध॒रस्य॑ दूषि॒तः। &amp;ldquo;तस्य॑ भी॒तस्य॒ स्वो म॑हि॒माप॑चक्रा॒म&amp;rdquo; इत्यत्र॒ तेन॑ भी॒ते स्व॑रचि॒ह्नं न लि॑खि॒तम्।   वॆबर-मूले द्विगुणितं ᳘ चिह्नं दृश्यते बहुत्र, यद् अग्रे so &amp;lsquo;gnímevā̀bʰī́kṣamāṇo vratamúpaiti इति दर्श्यते ऽनन्तनारायणेन।  वर्णव्यत्यासः  तछा᳘लो वा वि᳘मितं वा प्राची᳘नवंशम् मिन्वन्ति॥ / &amp;ldquo;tacʰā́lo vā vímitaṃ vā prācī́navaṃśam minvanti&amp;rdquo; इति weber-मूले । किन्तु, &amp;ldquo;तच्छा᳘लां वा&amp;rdquo; इति वंशीधरशास्त्रि-मूले ।  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A. THE VOW OF ABSTINENCE.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/1/</guid>
      <description>The ceremonies begin with the preparation of the sacrificial fires. [First, the fivefold lustration successively of the Āhavanīya and Dakshiṇāgni fire-places, to render them fit for receiving the fire from the Gārhapatya or householder&amp;rsquo;s fire, viz. by thrice sweeping the hearths; thrice besmearing them with gomaya; drawing three lines across them from west to east, or south to north, with the wooden sword (sphya); removing the dust from the lines with the thumb and ring-finger; and thrice sprinkling the lines with water 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>B. THE PRÂTAHSAVANA, OR MORNING-PRESSING.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Thereupon they sit down round the two press-boards 1. He (the Adhvaryu) then ties a piece of gold to that (nameless finger). For twofold, verily, is this; there is no third, namely, the truth and the untruth; the gods, forsooth, are the truth, and men are the untruth. And the gold has sprung from Agni&amp;rsquo;s seed: &amp;lsquo;With the truth I will touch the stalks, with the truth I will take hold of Soma,&amp;rsquo; thus he thinks, and therefore he ties a piece of gold to that (ring-finger).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C. THE SÂKAMEDHA OFFERINGSxa0[^fn_909].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, by means of the Varuṇapraghāsāḥ Prajāpati delivered the creatures from Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s noose; and those creatures of his were born without disease and blemish. Now with these Sākamedha offerings,&amp;ndash;therewith indeed the gods slew Vr̥tra, therewith they gained that supreme authority which they now wield; and so does he now therewith slay his wicked, spiteful enemy and gain the victory: this is why he performs these offerings in the fourth month (after the Varuṇapraghāsāḥ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CONSTRUCTION OF SHEDS, AND PREPARATION OF PRESSING-PLACE AND HEARTHS (DHISHNYAS).</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The sacrifice is a man; it is a man for the reason that a man spreads (prepares) it. In being spread it is made just as large 1 as a man: this is why the sacrifice is a man.  02 The Soma-cart (shed) is no other than his head, and has Vishṇu for its deity 2. And because Soma is therein&amp;ndash;Soma being havis (material for offering) for the gods&amp;ndash;therefore it is called Havirdhāna (receptacle of havis).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HIRANYAVATÎ-ÂHUTI,  OFFERING WITH GOLD; AND HOMAGE TO THE SOMA-COW.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Now Soma was in the sky, and the gods were here on earth. The gods desired,&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Would that Soma came to us: we might sacrifice with him, when come.&amp;rsquo; They created those two illusions, Suparṇī and Kadrū. In the chapter on the hearths (dhishṇya 1) it is set forth how that affair of Suparṇī and Kadrū came to pass.  02 Gāyatrī flew up to Soma for them. While she was carrying him off, the Gandharva Viśvāvasu stole him from her.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II. THE AGNIHOTRA  MORNING AND EVENING LIBATIONS;  THE AGNY-UPASTHÂNA  HOMAGE TO THE FIRES.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Prajāpati alone, indeed, existed here in the beginning. He considered, &amp;lsquo;How may I be reproduced?&amp;rsquo;  He toiled and performed acts of penance. He generated Agni from his mouth; and because he generated him from his mouth, therefore Agni is a consumer of food: and, verily, he who thus knows Agni to be a consumer of food, becomes himself a consumer of food.
02 He thus generated him first (agre) of the gods; and therefore (he is called) Agni, for agni (they say) is the same as agri.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>III. THE PINDAPITRIYAGÑA  OBLATION OF OBSEQUIAL CAKES TO THE FATHERS.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now the living beings once approached Prajāpati&amp;ndash;beings doubtless mean creatures&amp;ndash;and said, &amp;lsquo;Ordain unto us in what manner we are to live!&amp;rsquo; Thereupon the gods, being properly invested with the sacrificial cord 1 and bending the right knee, approached him. To them he said, &amp;lsquo;The sacrifice (shall be) your food; immortality your sap; and the sun your light!&amp;rsquo;  02 Then the fathers approached, wearing the cord on the right shoulder, and bending the left knee.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IV. THE ÂGRAYANESHTI  OFFERING OF FIRST-FRUITS.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Now Kahoḍa Kaushītaki spake, &amp;lsquo;This sap (of the plants) truly belongs to those two, heaven and earth: having offered of this sap to the gods, we will eat it.&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;That is why the offering of first-fruits is performed.&amp;rsquo;  02 And Yājñavalkya also spake:&amp;ndash;The gods and the Asuras, both of them sprung from Prajāpati, once contended for superiority. The Asuras then defiled, partly by magic, partly with poison, both kinds of plants&amp;ndash;those on which men and beasts subsist&amp;ndash;hoping that in this way they might over come the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OBLATION TO AGNI SVISHTAKRIT, [AND THE BRAHMAN&#39;S PORTIONS.]</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Now by means of the sacrifice the gods ascended to heaven. But the god who rules over  the cattle was left behind here: hence they call him Vāstavya, for he was then left behind on the (sacrificial) site 1 (vāstu).
02 The gods went on worshipping and toiling with the same (sacrifice) by which they had ascended to heaven. Now the god who rules over the cattle, and who was left behind here,&amp;ndash;  03 He saw (what occurred, and said), &amp;lsquo;I have been left behind: they are excluding me from the sacrifice!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PREPARATION OF THE SOMA ALTAR WITH THE HIGH ALTARxa0[^fn_290].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/1/</guid>
      <description>01  From that post which is the largest on the east side (of the hall) 1 he now strides three steps forwards (to the east), and there drives in a peg,&amp;ndash;this is the intermediate (peg) 2.  02 From that middle peg he strides fifteen steps to the right, and there drives in a peg,&amp;ndash;this is the right hip.  03 From that middle peg he strides fifteen steps northwards, and there drives in a peg,&amp;ndash;this is the left hip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PROCESSION AND ENTRANCE OF KING SOMA.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/4/</guid>
      <description>01  In the enclosed space (of the cart) 1 he (the Adhvaryu) lays down the black deer-skin, with the text (Vāj. S. IV, 30), &amp;lsquo;Thou art Aditi&amp;rsquo;s skin;&amp;rsquo; its significance is the same (as before) 2. Thereon he places him (Soma), with, &amp;lsquo;Seat thee on Aditi&amp;rsquo;s seat!&amp;rsquo; for Aditi being this (earth), and she being indeed a safe resting-place, he thereby places him on that safe resting-place: therefore he says, &amp;lsquo;Seat thee on Aditi&amp;rsquo;s seat!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SPECIAL PRELIMINARY RITES OF THE NEW-MOON SACRIFICE.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/4/</guid>
      <description>01  When Indra had hurled the thunderbolt at Vr̥tra, thinking himself to be the weaker, and fearing lest he had not brought him down, he concealed himself and went to the farthest distances 1. Now the gods knew that Vr̥tra had been slain and that Indra had concealed himself.  02 Agni of the deities, Hiraṇyastūpa 2 of the R̥shis, and the Br̥hatī of the metres, set about searching for him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SÛKTAVÂKA, SAMYUVÂKA, AND OFFERING OF REMAINSxa0[^fn_553].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/08/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/08/3/</guid>
      <description>01  He now separates the two spoons (juhū and upabhr̥t), with the text (Vāj. S. II, 15 a), &amp;lsquo;May I be victorious after the victory of Agni and Soma! with the impetus of the (sacrificial) food I urge myself on.&amp;rsquo; With his right hand he moves the juhū eastwards (from its usual place on the prastara-bunch upon the altar), with the text (ib. b), &amp;lsquo;May Agni and Soma drive him away who hates us, and whom  we hate!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE AFTER-OFFERINGS (ANUYÂGAS).</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/08/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/08/2/</guid>
      <description>01  They now remove two burning samidhs (from the Āhavanīya fire). That fire, indeed, is now worn out, (and therefore useless) for the after-offerings, since it has been carrying the sacrifice to the gods: &amp;lsquo;Let us perform the after-offerings in such (fire) as is not out-worn!&amp;rsquo; thus they think, and for this reason they remove those two burning samidhs (from the fire).  02 Thereupon they again move them close (to the fire).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE AGNI-PRANAYANA, OR LEADING FORWARD OF THE FIRExa0[^fn_321] TO THE HIGH ALTAR.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/2/</guid>
      <description>01  They put fire-wood on (the Āhavanīya fire), and prepare the underlayer (of gravel 1). He (the Adhvaryu) puts the butter on (the Gārhapatya to melt), and cleans both the dipping-spoon and the offering-spoon. Having then clarified the ghee, he ladles five times thereof (into the offering-spoon). When the fire-wood is ablaze-  02 They lift the (burning) fire-wood, and place it on the underlayer 2. Thereupon he says (to the Hotr̥), &amp;lsquo;Recite for Agni as he is taken forward 3!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE AGNISHTOMA. THE DÎKSHÂ,  CONSECRATION.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/1/</guid>
      <description>01  They choose a place of worship. Let them choose (the place) which lies highest, and above which no other part of the ground rises 1; for it was from thence that the gods ascended to heaven, and he who is consecrated indeed ascends to the gods. He thus sacrifices on a place of worship frequented by the gods; but were any other part of the ground to rise above it, he would indeed be lowered while sacrificing: let them therefore choose (the place) which lies highest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE ANIMAL SACRIFICExa0[^fn_428] TO AGNI AND SOMA.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Being about to cut the sacrificial stake, he offers 1 with a verse addressed to Vishṇu. For the stake belongs to Vishṇu; therefore he offers with a verse addressed to Vishṇu.  02 And again, why he offers with a verse addressed to Vishṇu&amp;ndash;Vishṇu being the sacrifice, he thus approaches the stake by means of the sacrifice: therefore he offers with a verse addressed to Vishṇu.  03 If he offers with the offering-spoon, he offers after taking ghee by four ladlings; and if he offers with the dipping-spoon, he offers after &amp;lsquo;cutting out&amp;rsquo; (some ghee from the pot) with the dipping-spoon,&amp;ndash;with the text (Vāj.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE AVÂNTARADÎKSHÂ,  INTERMEDIARY CONSECRATION.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/3/</guid>
      <description>01  When the gods had performed the guest-offering, discord arose between them. They allayed it by means of the Tānūnaptra (oaths). They desired an atonement for having spoken evil to one another; for they had appointed no other consecration-ceremony till the expiatory bath. They perceived this intermediate consecration 1.  02 By means of fire they enveloped (the body) with a skin. Now, fire being fervour, and the consecration being fervour, they thereby underwent an intermediate consecration; and because they underwent that  intermediate consecration, therefore this intermediary consecration (avāntaradīkshā, is performed).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE BUYING OF SOMA.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Having thrown the (earth of the) foot-print (into the pan), he (the Adhvaryu) washes his hands. Now as to why he washes his hands;&amp;ndash;clarified butter being a thunderbolt, and the Soma being seed, he washes his hands lest 1 he should injure the seed, Soma, with the thunderbolt, the ghee.  02 Thereupon he ties the piece of gold to this (finger 2). Now, twofold indeed is this (universe),&amp;ndash;there is no third,&amp;ndash;the truth and the untruth: the gods are the truth and men are the untruth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE CHIEF OFFERINGS.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, whoever exists, he, in being born, is born as (owing) a debt to the gods, to the R̥shis, to the fathers, and to men 1.  02 For, inasmuch as he is bound to sacrifice, for that reason he is born as (owing) a debt to the gods: hence when he sacrifices to them, when he makes  offerings to them, he does this (in discharge of his debt) to them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE DVÂDASÂHAxa0[^fn_935].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, at first the gods were all alike, all good. Of them, being all alike, all good, three desired, &amp;lsquo;May we be superior 1!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;Agni, Indra, and Sūrya.  02 They went on praising and toiling. They saw those Atigrāhyas 3, and drew (grah) them for themselves  over and above (ati): hence the name Atigrāhyas. They became superior, even as they are now superior 4 and verily he becomes superior for whomsoever, knowing this, they draw those cups of Soma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE DÂKSHÂYANA SACRIFICE.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/4/</guid>
      <description>Here also two days were, as a rule, required for the performance, both at full and new moon; but while, at the ordinary sacrifice,
At full moon some authorities add a special ishṭi to Indra Vimr̥dh (&amp;rsquo;the Averter of evil&amp;rsquo;). The new-moon performance concludes with libations of whey to the divine coursers (the horses of the gods); and, optionally, with an ishṭi to Āditya.
The performance of the Dākshāyaṇa sacrifice was held to be obligatory only for a period of fifteen years (see XI, 1, 2, 13), whereas the ordinary new and full-moon offerings had to be performed for double that period from the setting up of the sacred fires.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE FORE-OFFERINGS (PRAYÂGAS).</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/2/</guid>
      <description>01  [The Hotr̥ continues], &amp;lsquo;May Agni, the priest (hotr̥), know (undertake) Agni&amp;rsquo;s priestly duty (hautram),&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;thereby he says &amp;lsquo;may Agni, as Hotr̥, know this!&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Agni&amp;rsquo;s priestly duty&amp;rsquo; he says, because it is his duty that he must know;&amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo;that means of salvation 1,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;the means of salvation, assuredly, is the sacrifice: &amp;lsquo;may he know the sacrifice&amp;rsquo; is what he thereby says.&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Favourable to thee, O Sacrificer, is  the deity!&amp;rsquo; by this he says &amp;lsquo;favourable is the deity to thee, O Sacrificer, whose Hotr̥ is Agni 2!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE GAVÂM AYANAxa0[^fn_988].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, they who sit (sacrificing) for a year, by means of six months go to him that burns yonder:  so it is told on the part of the Sāman, in as much as it is made of the form of that (sun) it is told on the part of the R̥k 1; and now in like manner on the part of the Yajus, by means of preparatory rite, when they draw that (graha) 2, they thereby also go to him (the sun).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE IDÂ.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/08/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/08/1/</guid>
      <description>01  In the morning they brought to Manu 1 water for washing, just as now also they (are wont to) bring (water) for washing the hands. When he was washing himself, a fish came into his hands.  02 It spake to him the word, &amp;lsquo;Rear me, I will save thee!&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Wherefrom wilt thou save me?&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;A flood will carry away all these creatures 2: from that I will save thee!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE KINDLING OF THE FIRE, THE PRAVARA, AND THE TWO LIBATIONS (ÂGHÂRA) OF BUTTER.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/5/</guid>
      <description>01  With the fire-wood (idhma, lighting material) the Adhvaryu lights (indh) the fire: hence it is called fire-wood. And with the kindling verses (sāmidhenī) the Hotr̥ kindles (sam-indh, to make blaze): hence they are called kindling verses.  02 He (the Adhvaryu 1) says (to the Hotr̥): &amp;lsquo;Recite to the fire as it is being kindled!&amp;rsquo; for it is to the fire, when it is being kindled, that he recites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE OBLATIONS.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/1/</guid>
      <description>01  When he has taken out the Āhavanīya fire 1, he performs the Full-offering 2. The reason why  he performs the full-offering is that he thereby causes that Agni to become an eater of food for his own self; that he thereby offers food to him. Even as (a mother or cow) would offer the breast to a new-born child or calf, so does he thereby offer food to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE PATNÎSAMYÂGAS. CONCLUDING CEREMONIES.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/09/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/09/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Being about to perform the patnīsaṁyājas 1, they betake themselves back to the Gārhapatya fire. The Adhvaryu takes the juhū and sruva, the Hotr̥ the veda, and the Āgnīdhra the butter-(melting) pot.  02 Here now the Adhvaryu, according to some, passes the Āhavanīya on the east side. Let him not, however, do this; for were he to walk on that side, he would be outside the sacrifice.  03 According to others, the Adhvaryu walks (so as to pass) behind the (sacrificer&amp;rsquo;s) wife 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE PREPARATION OF THE ALTAR.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Fourfold, namely, was Agni (fire) at first. Now that Agni whom they at first chose for the office of Hotr̥ priest passed away. He also whom they chose the second time passed away. He also whom they chose the third time passed away 1. Thereupon the one who still constitutes the fire in our own time, concealed himself from fear. He entered into the waters. Him the gods discovered and brought forcibly away from the waters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE PRÂYANÎYESHTI,  OPENING-SACRIFICE.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/3/</guid>
      <description>01  He prepares the Prāyaṇīya rice-pap for Aditi. Now while the gods were spreading (performing) the sacrifice on this (earth) they excluded her (the earth) from the sacrifice. She thought, &amp;lsquo;How is it that, in spreading the sacrifice on me, they should exclude me from the sacrifice?&amp;rsquo; and confounded their sacrifice: they knew not that sacrifice.  02 They said, &amp;lsquo;How comes it that our sacrifice was confounded, when we spread it on this (earth)?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE PUNARÂDHEYA OR RE-ESTABLISHMENT OF THE SACRED FIRESxa0[^fn_707].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Now Varuṇa established this (fire), being desirous of sovereignty. He obtained sovereignty; and, accordingly, whether one (who has established the fires) knows (this) or not, they call him &amp;lsquo;king Varuṇa.&amp;rsquo; Soma (established the fire), being desirous of glory. He became glorious, and, accordingly, whether one obtains a hold on Soma, or whether  one does not, they both obtain (glory),&amp;ndash;for it is glory that people thereby get to see.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE SOMA FEAST.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/3/</guid>
      <description>01  They (the priests) are wakened (towards morning). Having touched water 1, they proceed together to the Āgnīdhra (fire-house) and take the portions of ghee (for the Savanīya animal offerings). Having taken the portions of ghee, they betake themselves (to the high altar). When they have deposited the ghee,&amp;ndash;  02 He (the Adhvaryu) takes down the king (Soma) 2. Now this (earth) is a safe resting-place, and the birth-place of living beings; it is to this safe resting-place that he now takes him down; he spreads him thereon, produces him therefrom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE TWO BUTTER-PORTIONS (ÂGYABHÂGA) TO AGNI AND SOMA.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Now the Seasons were desirous to have a share in the sacrifice among the gods, and said, &amp;lsquo;Let us share in the sacrifice! Do not exclude us from the sacrifice! Let us have a share in the sacrifice!&amp;rsquo;  02 The gods, however, did not approve of this. The gods not approving, the Seasons went to the Asuras, the malignant, spiteful enemies of the gods.  03 Those (Asuras) then throve in such a manner that they (the gods) heard of it; for even while the foremost (of the Asuras) were still ploughing and sowing, those behind them were already engaged in reaping and threshing: indeed even without tilling the plants ripened forthwith for them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE TÂNÛNAPTRA,  COVENANT OF TANÛNAPÂTxa0[^fn_247].</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/2/</guid>
      <description>01  When the gods had performed the guest-offering, discord befell them. They separated into four different parties, unwilling to yield to each other&amp;rsquo;s excellence,&amp;ndash;Agni, with the Vasus, Soma with the Rudras, Varuṇa with the Ādityas, and Indra with the Maruts. Br̥haspati with the All-gods, say some 1, but, indeed, those who separated into four parties were &amp;lsquo;all the gods.&amp;rsquo; When they were separated, the Asura-Rakshas came after them and entered between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE UPASADS,  HOMAGES.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily the Upasads (homages or sieges) are the neck of the sacrifice, and the Pravargya is its head. Hence when it is performed with the Pravargya 1,  they perform the Upasads 2 after performing the Pravargya, and thereby they put the neck in its place.
02 The anuvākyās (invitatory prayers) in the forenoon are the yājyās (offering prayers) in the afternoon; and the yājyās are the anuvākyās 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE VAISARGINA OFFERINGS AND LEADING FORWARD OF AGNI AND SOMA.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily he who consecrates himself, consecrates himself for the sake of this All; for he consecrates himself for the sacrifice, and this All indeed results from 1 the sacrifice; having prepared the sacrifice for which he consecrates himself, he now sets free (or produces) this All.  02 The reason why he performs the Vaisarjina offerings is this. They are called Vaisarjina, because he sets free (vi-sarj) this All; wherefore let him who takes part in the rite 2 touch (the sacrificer) from behind; but if he have to go elsewhere (on business) he need not heed this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE VASATÎVARÎ WATER.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, when the head of the sacrifice (victim) was struck off, its sap, running, entered the waters. It is by that very sap that those waters flow; that very sap is believed to be flowing there 1.  02 And when he goes for the Vasatīvarī water, he fetches that same sap and puts it into the sacrifice, and makes the sacrifice sapful; this is why he goes for the Vasatīvarī water.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE ÂTITHYA,  GUEST-OFFERING (HOSPITABLE RECEPTION GIVEN TO KING SOMA).</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/04/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, the guest-offering is the head of the sacrifice, and the Prāyaṇīya and Udayanīya are its arms. But the arms are on both sides of the head: therefore those two oblations, the Prāyaṇīya and Udayanīya, are on both sides of the guest-offering.  02 Now as to why it is called &amp;lsquo;guest-offering.&amp;rsquo; He, the purchased Soma, truly comes as his (the sacrificer&amp;rsquo;s) guest,&amp;ndash;to him (is offered) that (hospitable reception): even as for a king or a Brāhman one would cook a large ox or a large he-goat&amp;ndash;for that is human (fare offered to a guest), and the oblation is that of the gods&amp;ndash;so he prepares for him that guest-offering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Thereupon he takes the winnowing basket and the Agnihotra ladle 1, with the text (Vāj. S. I, 6 b): &amp;lsquo;For the work (I take) you, for pervasion (or accomplishment) you two!&amp;rsquo; For the sacrifice is a work: hence, in saying &amp;lsquo;for the work you two,&amp;rsquo; he says, &amp;lsquo;for the sacrifice.&amp;rsquo; And &amp;lsquo;for pervasion you two,&amp;rsquo; he says,  because he, as it were, pervades (goes through, accomplishes) the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/3/</guid>
      <description>01  He now prepares two strainers (pavitra) 1, with the text (Vāj. S. I, 12 a): &amp;lsquo;Purifiers (or strainers, pavitra) are ye, and belonging to Vishṇu!&amp;rsquo; For Vishṇu is the sacrifice; so that he thereby says, &amp;lsquo;You belong to the sacrifice.&amp;rsquo;  02 Two there are of them: for means of cleansing (pavitra) is this (wind) which here ventilates (pavate); and this, it is true, ventilates as one only; but on entering into man, it becomes a forward and a backward one, and they are these two, to wit, the prāṇa (breathing out) and the udāna (breathing up or in) 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/01/4/</guid>
      <description>01  He now takes the black antelope skin 1, for completeness of the sacrifice. For once upon a time the sacrifice escaped the gods, and having become a black antelope roamed about. The gods having thereupon found it and stripped it of its skin, they brought it (the skin) away with them.  02 Its white and black hairs represent the R̥c-verses and the Sāman-verses; to wit, the white the Sāman and the black the R̥c; or conversely, the black the Sāman and the white the R̥c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Now the one (viz. the Āgnīdhra) puts the potsherds on (the Gārhapatya fire); the other (viz. the Adhvaryu) the two mill-stones (on the black antelope skin): these two acts are done simultaneously. The reason why they are done simultaneously (is this):  02 The head of this sacrifice is (represented by) the rice-cake 1: for those potsherds (kapāla), no doubt, are to this (rice-cake) what the skull bones (kapāla) are to the head, and the ground rice is  nothing else than the brain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/2/</guid>
      <description>01  He pours (the ground rice) into that which contains the strainers&amp;ndash;viz. into a dish (pātrī) on which he has laid the two strainers&amp;ndash;with the text (Vāj. S. I, 21): &amp;lsquo;At the impulse of the divine Savitr̥ I pour thee out, with the arms of the Aśvins, with the hands of Pūshan!&amp;rsquo; The import of this formula is the same (as before, I, 1, 2, 17).  02 He now sits down somewhere inside the altar (vedi) 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/4/</guid>
      <description>01  When Indra hurled the thunderbolt at Vr̥tra, that hurled one became fourfold. Of (three parts of) it the wooden sword (sphya) represents one-third or thereabouts, the sacrificial post one-third or thereabouts, and the chariot one-third or thereabouts. That piece, moreover, with which he struck him, was broken off (śr̥); and on falling down it became an arrow (śara): hence the designation arrow, because it was broken off. And in this way the thunderbolt became fourfold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/02/5/</guid>
      <description>01  The gods and the Asuras, both of them sprung from Prajāpati, were contending for superiority. Then the gods were worsted, and the Asuras thought: &amp;lsquo;To us alone assuredly belongs this world!  02 They thereupon said: &amp;lsquo;Well then, let us divide this world between us; and having divided it, let us subsist thereon!&amp;rsquo; They accordingly set about dividing it with ox-hides from west to east.  03 The gods then heard of this, and said: &amp;lsquo;The Asuras are actually dividing this earth: come, let us go to where the Asuras are dividing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He (the Āgnīdhra) now brushes the spoons 1 (with the grass-ends). The reason why he brushes  the spoons is that the course 2 pursued among the gods is in accordance with that pursued among men. Now, when the serving up of food is at hand among men,&amp;ndash;
02 They rinse the vessels, and having rinsed them, they serve up the food with them: in the same way is treated the sacrifice to the gods, that is to say, the cooked oblations and the prepared altar; and those vessels of theirs, the sacrificial spoons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now the sacrifice is the man. The sacrifice is the man for the reason that the man spreads (performs) it; and that in being spread it is made of exactly the same extent as the man 1: this is the reason why the sacrifice is the man.  02 The juhū (spoon) further belongs to that (man-shaped sacrifice), and so does the upabhr̥t; and the dhruvā 2 represents its trunk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The Adhvaryu takes the sprinkling-water, and sprinkles in the first place the fire-wood 1, with the  text (Vāj. S. II, 1), &amp;lsquo;A black deer, living in the den, art thou 2; I sprinkle thee, agreeable to Agni!&amp;rsquo; He thereby makes it sacrificially pure for Agni.
02 He then sprinkles he altar, with the text (Vāj. S. II, 1), &amp;lsquo;Thou art the altar; I sprinkle thee, agreeable to the barhis (sacrificial-grass covering)!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/03/4/</guid>
      <description>01  They should be green (fresh); for that is (what constitutes) their living element, by that they are vigorous, by that possessed of strength: for this reason they should be green.  02 The middle stick he lays down first (on the west side of the fire), with the text (Vāj. S. II, 3), &amp;lsquo;May the Gandharva Viśvāvasu 1 lay thee around  for the security of the All! Thou art a fence to the sacrificer, thou (art) Agni, invoked and worthy of invocation!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He recites after uttering (the syllable) &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ!&amp;rsquo; Sacrifice, they say, is not (performed) without the Sāman; and neither is the Sāman chanted without &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ&amp;rsquo; having been uttered. By his uttering &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ!&amp;rsquo; the peculiar nature (rūpam) of the word &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ&amp;rsquo; is produced (in the sacrifice); and by the sacred syllable (om) it assumes the nature of the Sāman. By uttering &amp;lsquo;Om! Om 1!&amp;rsquo; this his entire sacrifice becomes endowed with the Sāman.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now in former times the gods appointed Agni to the chief (office), namely, that of Hotr̥; and having appointed him to the chief (office) saying &amp;lsquo;do thou carry this our oblation!&amp;rsquo; they cheered him up, saying, &amp;lsquo;Surely, thou art vigorous; surely, thou art equal to this!&amp;rsquo; thereby endowing him with vigour, even as in our own days, when they appoint any one from among their kinsmen to the chief (office), they cheer him up saying &amp;lsquo;surely, thou art vigorous; surely, thou art equal to this!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The fire that has been kindled by means of the kindling verses, assuredly, blazes more brightly than any other fire; for, indeed, it is unassailable, unapproachable.  02 And in like manner as the fire blazes when kindled by means of the kindling verses, so also blazes the priest (brāhmaṇa) that knows and recites the kindling verses; for, indeed, he is unassailable, unapproachable.  03 He recites, &amp;lsquo;Pra vaḥ 1;&amp;rsquo; for the (word) prāṇa contains the syllable pra (&amp;lsquo;forwards;&amp;rsquo; or, is directed forwards):.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/4/</guid>
      <description>01  That same fire, then, they have kindled, (thinking), &amp;lsquo;In it, when kindled, we will sacrifice to the gods.&amp;rsquo; In it, indeed, he makes these two first oblations 1 to Mind and Speech (or, Voice); for mind and speech, when yoked together, convey the sacrifice to the gods.  02 Now, what is performed (with formulas, pronounced) in a low voice, by that the mind conveys the sacrifice to the gods; and what is performed (with formulas) distinctly uttered by speech, by that the speech conveys the sacrifice to the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/04/5/</guid>
      <description>01  When he (the Adhvaryu) is about to make the second libation with the offering-spoon (sruc), he (twice) lays his joined hands (añjali) on the ground before the two offering-spoons (juhū and upabhr̥t), with the formulas (Vāj. S. II, 7 b), &amp;lsquo;Adoration to the gods!&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Svadhā to the fathers!&amp;rsquo; Thereby he propitiates the gods and the fathers, now that  he is about to perform the duties of the sacrificial priest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He (the Adhvaryu) now utters his call for the Pravara (choosing of the Hotr̥) 1. The reason why he utters his call, is that the (Adhvaryu&amp;rsquo;s) call is  the sacrifice: &amp;lsquo;having bespoke the sacrifice, I will choose the Hotr̥,&amp;rsquo; thus (he thinks, and) for this reason he utters his call for the Pravara.
02 He utters his call after taking the fuel-band; for if the Adhvaryu were to utter his call without taking hold of the sacrifice, he would either be unsteady or meet with some other ailment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The fore-offerings (prayāja), assuredly, are the seasons: hence there are five of them, for there are five seasons.  02 The gods and the Asuras, both of them sprang from Prajāpati, were once contending for this sacrifice, (which is) their father Prajāpati, the year: &amp;lsquo;Ours it (he) shall be!&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Ours it (he) shall be!&amp;rsquo; they said.  03 Then the gods went on praising and toiling. They saw these fore-offerings and worshipped with them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/05/4/</guid>
      <description>01  He (accordingly) pronounces the offering-prayer to the Samidhs (kindling-sticks). The Samidhs (kindlers), doubtless, are the breaths (vital airs), and he thereby kindles the breaths; for this man (the sacrificer) is kindled (animated) by his breaths: hence if he (the sacrificer) be burning (with fever, &amp;amp;c.), he (the Adhvaryu) will say, &amp;lsquo;Stroke (thyself)!&amp;rsquo; If he be hot, then one may feel confident, for then he is kindled; and if he be cold, then one need hope no longer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, by means of the sacrifice the gods made that conquest (of the world of heaven). When they had conquered, they said, &amp;lsquo;How may this (celestial region) be made unattainable by men?&amp;rsquo; They then sipped the sap of the sacrifice, as bees would suck out honey; and having drained the sacrifice and effaced the traces of it with the (sacrificial) post 1, they  concealed themselves: and because they effaced (ayopayan, viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/06/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Tvashṭr̥ had a three-headed, six-eyed son. He had three mouths; and because he was thus shaped, his name was Viśvarūpa (&amp;lsquo;All-shape&amp;rsquo;).  02 One of his mouths was Soma-drinking, one spirit-drinking, and one for other kinds of food. Indra hated him and cut off those heads of his.  03 Now from the one which was Soma-drinking, a hazel-cock (francoline partridge) sprang forth; whence the latter is of brownish colour, for king Soma is brown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He (the Adhvaryu) drives the calves away (from the cows) with a parṇa branch 1. The reason why he drives the calves away with a parṇa branch is this. When the Gāyatrī flew towards Soma (the moon), a footless archer aiming at her while she was carrying him off, severed one of the feathers (parṇa) either of the Gāyatrī or of king Soma 2; and on falling down it became a parṇa (palāśa) tree; whence its name parṇa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/07/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Prajāpati conceived a passion for his own  daughter,&amp;ndash;either the Sky or the Dawn 1. &amp;lsquo;May I pair with her!&amp;rsquo; thus (thinking) he united with her.
02 This, assuredly, was a sin in the eyes of the gods. &amp;lsquo;He who acts thus towards his own daughter, our sister, [commits a sin],&amp;rsquo; they thought.  03 The gods then said to this god who rules over the beasts (Rudra) 2, &amp;lsquo;This one, surely, commits a sin who acts thus towards his own daughter, our sister.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/09/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/09/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Now 1 when (the Adhvaryu) says, &amp;lsquo;The divine Hotr̥s are summoned for the proclamation of success,  the human one is called upon for the song of praise (sūkta-vāka);&amp;rsquo; and when the Hotr̥ thereupon recites, he recites good words only 2: he thereby invokes a blessing on the sacrificer. It is indeed after the sacrifice that he thus invokes a blessing. A twofold reason there is for his invoking the blessing after the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/09/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/01/09/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The sacrifice being now complete, he (the Adhvaryu) walks round (the fire) to the south, and pours out a vessel (of water); for thus it is (poured out) towards north: therefore he pours it out after walking round to the south, He who sacrifices, doubtless, sacrifices with a desire that he also may obtain a place in the world of the gods. That sacrifice of his then goes forth towards the world of the gods: after it follows the fee which he gives (to the priests), and holding on to the priests&amp;rsquo; fee (follows) the sacrificer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/1/</guid>
      <description>The normal performance of the Agnyādhāna, as that of the full and new-moon offerings, requires two days; the first of which is taken up with preliminary rites, while the second&amp;ndash;that is, the first day of the respective half-moon&amp;ndash;is devoted to the chief ceremonies, beginning with the production of the sacred fire by friction. (See II, 1, 4, 8 seq.)
After the sacrificer has chosen his four officiating priests&amp;ndash;viz. the Brahman, Hotr̥, Adhvaryu, and Āgnīdhra (or Agnīdh)&amp;ndash;he proceeds, together with them, to erect the two sheds or &amp;lsquo;firehouses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/2/</guid>
      <description>01  He may set up the two fires 1 under the Kr̥ttikās; for they, the Kr̥ttikās, are doubtless Agni&amp;rsquo;s asterism, so that if he sets up his fires under Agni&amp;rsquo;s asterism, (he will bring about) a correspondence (between his fires and the asterism): for this reason he may set up his fires under the Kr̥ttikās.  02 Moreover, the other lunar asterisms (consist of) one, two, three or four (stars), so that the Kr̥ttikās are the most numerous (of asterisms) 2: hence he thereby obtains an abundance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The spring, the summer, and the rains, these seasons (represent) the gods; and the autumn, the winter, and the dewy season represent the fathers. That half-moon which increases represents the gods, and that which decreases represents the fathers. The day represents the gods, and the night represents the fathers. And, further, the forenoon represents the gods, and the afternoon the fathers.  02 Those seasons, then, are the gods and the fathers; and whosoever, knowing this, invokes them as the gods and fathers, with his invocation of the gods the gods comply, and with his invocation of the fathers the fathers comply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/01/4/</guid>
      <description>01  On the day preceding his Agnyādheya, he (the sacrificer with his wife) should take his food in the day-time. For the gods know the minds of man: they are, therefore, aware that his Agnyādheya is to take place on the morrow; and all the gods betake themselves to his house and stay (upa-vas) in his house; whence this day is called upavasatha (fast-day) 1.  02 Now, as it would be unbecoming for him to take food before men (who are staying with him as his guests) have eaten; how much more would it be so, if he were to take food before the gods have eaten: let him therefore take his food in the day-time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/02/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, in performing that sacrifice, they slay it; and in pressing out the king (Soma), they slay him; and in quieting and immolating the victim, they slay it. The haviryajña they slay with the mortar and pestle, and with the two mill-stones.  02 When slain, that sacrifice was no longer vigorous. By means of dakshiṇās (gifts to the priests) the gods again invigorated it: hence the name dakshiṇā, because thereby they invigorated (dakshay) that  (sacrifice).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/1/</guid>
      <description>01  The Agnihotra, doubtless, is the Sun. It is because he rose in front (agre) of that offering 1, that the Agnihotra is the Sun.  02 When he offers in the evening after sunset, he does so thinking, &amp;lsquo;I will offer, while he is here, who is this (offering);&amp;rsquo; and when he offers in the morning before sunrise, he does so thinking, &amp;lsquo;I will offer, while he is here, who is this (offering):&amp;rsquo; and for this reason, they say, the Agnihotra is the Sun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, in him that exists 1, these deities reside, to wit, Indra, king Yama, Naḍa the Naishadha 2 (king), Anaśnat Sāṅgamana, and Asat Pāṁsava.  02 Now Indra, in truth, is the same as the Āhavanīya; and king Yama is the same as the Gārhapatya; and Naḍa Naishadha is the same as the Anvāhāryapacana (Dakshiṇa fire); and because day by day they take that (fire) to the south, therefore indeed they say that day by day Naḍa Naishadha carries king Yama 3 (further) south.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Now when Prajāpati, in creating living beings, created Agni, the latter, as soon as born, sought to burn everything here: and so everybody tried to get out of his way 1. The creatures then existing sought to crush him. Being unable to endure this, he went to man.  02 He said, &amp;lsquo;I cannot endure this: come, let me enter into thee! Having reproduced me, maintain me; and as thou wilt reproduce and maintain me in this world, even so will I reproduce and maintain thee in yonder world!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/03/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Once on a time the gods deposited with Agni all their beasts, both domestic and wild; either because they were about to engage in battle or from a desire of free scope, or because they thought that he (Agni) would protect them as the best protector.  02 Now Agni coveted them, and seizing them he entered the night with them. &amp;lsquo;Let us go back thither,&amp;rsquo; said the gods, and betook themselves to where Agni was concealed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/04/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Now after the performance of the Agnihotra he (optionally 1) .approaches the fires with (Vāj. S. III, 37), &amp;lsquo;Earth! ether! sky!&amp;rsquo; In saying &amp;lsquo;Earth! ether! sky!&amp;rsquo; he renders his speech auspicious by means of the truth, and with that (speech) thus rendered propitious he invokes a blessing:&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;May I be well supplied with offspring!&amp;rsquo; whereby he prays for offspring; &amp;lsquo;&amp;ndash;well supplied with men!&amp;rsquo; whereby he prays for men (heroes); &amp;lsquo;&amp;ndash;well supplied with viands!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now it was by means of the Vaiśvadeva that Prajāpati produced living beings. The beings produced by him ate (ghas) Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s barley corn; for originally the barley belonged to Varuṇa. And from their eating Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s barley corn the name Varuṇapraghāsāḥ (is derived).  02 Varuṇa seized them; and on being seized by Varuṇa, they became rent all over 1; and they lay and sat them down breathing in and breathing out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, by means of the Great Oblation the gods slew Vr̥tra 1; by means of it they gained that supreme authority which they now wield; and so does he (the Sacrificer) thereby now slay his wicked, spiteful enemy, and gain the victory: this is why he performs this sacrifice.  02 The mode of its performance (is as follows): They raise an uttara-vedi 2; they use clotted butter 3; and they churn the fire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, by means of the Great Oblation the gods slew Vr̥tra, and gained that supreme authority which they now wield. And by means of the sacrifice to the fathers they then recalled to life those of them that had been slain in this battle; and they, indeed, were the fathers: hence the name Pitr̥yajña 1 (sacrifice to the Manes).  02 Now the spring, the summer, and the rainy season,&amp;ndash;they are those who vanquished (Vr̥tra); and the autumn, the winter, and the dewy season,&amp;ndash;they are those whom they (the gods) recalled to life 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, by means of the Great Oblation the gods slew Vr̥tra; by it they gained that supreme authority which they now wield. Now whichever of them were hit by (the Asuras’) arrows in that battle, those same darts they extracted, those they pulled out, by performing the Tryambaka-offerings.  02 And, accordingly, when he performs those offerings, he either does so hoping that thus no arrow  (misfortune) will hit any of his, or because the gods did so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, imperishable is the righteousness of him that offers the Seasonal sacrifices; for such a one gains the year, and hence there is no cessation for him. He gains it (the year) in three divisions, he conquers it in three divisions. The year means the whole, and the whole is imperishable (without end): hence his righteousness is indeed imperishable. Moreover, he thereby becomes a Season, and as such goes to the gods; but there is no perishableness in the gods, and hence there is imperishable righteousness for him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/06/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Now when it is said, that the gods, by means of the Sākamedha -offerings, slew Vr̥tra and gained that supreme authority which they now wield,&amp;ndash;it is rather by means of all the Seasonal sacrifices that the gods slew Vr̥tra; it is by all of them that they gained that supreme authority which they now wield.  02 They spake, &amp;lsquo;With what king, with what leader 1 shall we fight?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Let him perform the rite of consecration (dīkshā) 1 in the afternoon. Previously to the shaving  of his hair and beard he may eat of what he likes, or whatever comes to hand; for hereafter his food consists of fast-milk (vrata) only. But, if he does not care to eat, he need not eat anything.
02 Thereupon they enclose a place 2 north of the hall, and place a vessel of water in it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Having brought water forward 1, he takes out (the material for) a cake on eleven potsherds for Agni and Vishṇu; for Agni is all the deities, since it is in Agni that offering is made to all the deities. Moreover Agni is the lower half, and Vishṇu is the upper half of the sacrifice: &amp;lsquo;I will become consecrated after encompassing all the deities, after encompassing the entire sacrifice,&amp;rsquo; thus he thinks, and hence there is a cake on eleven potsherds for Agni and Vishṇu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/01/4/</guid>
      <description>01  All formulas of the consecration are audgrabhaṇa (elevatory), since he who is consecrated elevates himself (ud-grabh) from this world to the world of the gods. He elevates himself by means of these same formulas, and therefore they say that all formulas of the consecration are &amp;lsquo;audgrabhaṇa.&amp;rsquo; Now they also (specially) designate these intermediate ones as &amp;lsquo;audgrabhaṇa,&amp;rsquo; because these are libations 1, and a libation is a sacrifice. For the muttering of a sacrificial formula is an occult (form of sacrifice), but a libation is a direct (form of) sacrifice: hence it is by this same sacrifice that he elevates himself from this world to the world of the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/1/</guid>
      <description>01  South of the Āhavanīya he spreads two black antelope skins on the ground, with the neck parts towards the east: thereon he consecrates him. If there are two (skins), they are an image of these two worlds (heaven and earth), and thus he consecrates him on these two worlds.  02 They are joined (fitted) together along their edge 1, for these two worlds are also, as it were, joined together at their edge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/02/2/</guid>
      <description>01  He maintains silence; and silently he remains seated till sunset. The reason why he maintains silence is this:  02 By means of the sacrifice the gods gained that supreme authority which they now wield. They spake, &amp;lsquo;How can this (world) of ours be made unattainable to men?&amp;rsquo; They sipped the sap of the sacrifice, even as bees would suck out honey; and having drained the sacrifice and scattered it by means of the sacrificial post, they disappeared: and because they scattered (yopaya, viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He follows her, stepping into seven foot-prints of hers 1; he thereby takes possession of her: that  is why he steps into seven of her foot-prints. For when the metres were produced from Vāc (speech), the one consisting of seven feet, the Śakvarī, was the last (highest) of them. It is that (metre) he now draws down towards himself from above: this is why he steps into seven of her foot-prints.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/03/3/</guid>
      <description>01  He bargains for the king (Soma); and because he bargains for the king, therefore any and everything is vendible here. He says, &amp;lsquo;Soma-seller, is thy king Soma for sale?&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;He is for sale,&amp;rsquo; says the Soma-seller.&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;I will buy him of thee!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Buy him!&amp;rsquo; says the Soma-seller.&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;I will buy him of thee for one-sixteenth (of the cow).&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;King Soma, surely, is worth more than that!&amp;rsquo; says the Soma-seller.&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Yea, King Soma is worth more than that; but great, surely, is the greatness of the cow,&amp;rsquo; says the Adhvaryu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/05/4/</guid>
      <description>01  It is for a twofold reason that the sounding-holes are dug. The cart-shed, truly, is the head of the sacrificer; and what four holes there are here in the head&amp;ndash;namely, these two and these two 1&amp;ndash;those he thereby makes: for this reason he digs the sounding-holes.  02 Now the gods and the Asuras, both of them sprung from Prajāpati, were contending. The Asuras then by way of witchcraft buried charms 2 within these worlds, thinking, &amp;lsquo;Peradventure we may thus overcome the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/1/</guid>
      <description>01  The Sadas 1 is no other than his (Vishṇu, the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;s) belly; therefore they feed (drink) in the  Sadas; for whatever food is eaten here on earth, all that settles down in the belly. And because all the gods sat (sad) in it, therefore it is called sadas: and so do these Brāhmans of every family now sit therein. By way of deity it belongs to Indra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/06/2/</guid>
      <description>01  The Dhishṇya-hearths 1, forsooth, are no other  than its (the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;s) congeners 2. They have the same marks, and those which have the same marks are congeners; and these, then, are those (corresponding limbs) of its trunk.
02 Now Soma was in heaven, and the gods were here on earth. The gods desired, &amp;lsquo;Would that Soma might come to us; we might sacrifice with him, when come.&amp;rsquo; They produced those two illusions, Suparṇī and Kadrū 3; Suparṇī, forsooth, was Vāc (speech) 4, and Kadrū was this (earth).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He takes the spade, with (Vāj. S. VI, 1), &amp;lsquo;I take thee, at the impulse of the divine Savitr̥, with the arms of the Aśvins, with the hands of Pūshan: thou art a woman.&amp;rsquo; The significance of that formula is the same (as before); and that spade (abhri, fem.) is indeed female: therefore he says &amp;rsquo;thou art a woman.&amp;rsquo;  02 He thus draws the outline of the hole (for the stake 1), with, &amp;lsquo;Herewith I cut off the necks of  the Rakshas!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, as large as the altar is, so large is the earth. The sacrificial stakes are thunderbolts; and by means of these thunderbolts he obtains possession of this earth, and excludes his enemies from sharing therein. Hence there are eleven stakes, and the twelfth lies aside rough-hewn; he puts it down south (of the altar). The reason why the twelfth lies aside is this.  02 Now the gods, while performing this sacrifice,  were afraid of an attack from the Asura-Rakshas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/3/</guid>
      <description>01  There are both an animal and a sacrificial stake, for never do they immolate an animal without a stake. And as to why this is so:&amp;ndash;well, animals did not at first submit thereto that they should become food, as they are now become food; for just as man here walks two-footed and erect, so did they walk two-footed and erect.  02 Then the gods perceived that thunderbolt, to wit, the sacrificial stake; they raised it, and from fear thereof they (the animals) shrunk together and thus became four-footed, and thus became food, as they are now become food, for they submitted thereto: wherefore they immolate the animal only at a stake and never without a stake.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/07/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Having made a noose, he throws it over (the victim) with (Vāj. S. VI, 8), &amp;lsquo;With the noose of sacred order I bind thee, O oblation to the gods!&amp;rsquo; for that rope, forsooth, is Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s: therefore he thus binds it with the noose of sacred order, and thus that rope of Varuṇa does not injure it.  02 &amp;lsquo;Be bold, O man 1!&amp;rsquo; for at first man dared not 2 to approach it (the victim); but now that he thus binds it with the noose of sacred order, as an oblation to the gods, man dares to approach it: therefore he says, &amp;lsquo;Be bold, O man!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Thereupon the Hotr̥, having sat down on the Hotr̥&amp;rsquo;s seat whereon he sits down after being chosen 1,  urges, and thus urged the Adhvaryu takes the two spoons.
02 They then proceed with the Āprī (verses). The reason why they proceed with the Āprīs is this. With his whole mind, with his whole self, forsooth, he who consecrates himself prepares and endeavours to prepare the sacrifice. His self is, as it were, emptied out; with those Āprīs they fill it again; and because they fill 2 it therewith, therefore they are called Āprī.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/2/</guid>
      <description>01  When he (the slaughterer) announces, &amp;lsquo;The victim has been quieted!&amp;rsquo; the Adhvaryu says, &amp;lsquo;Neshṭar, lead up the lady!&amp;rsquo; The Neshṭr̥ leads up the (sacrificer&amp;rsquo;s) wife bearing a vessel of water for washing the feet.  02 He makes her say (Vāg . S. VI, 12), &amp;lsquo;Homage be to thee, O wide-stretched!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;the wide-stretched one, forsooth, is the sacrifice; for they stretch the sacrifice (over the sacrificial ground):  hence the wide-stretched one is the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/3/</guid>
      <description>01  For the same deity for which there is a victim, he subsequently prepares a sacrificial cake 1. The reason why he subsequently prepares a cake is this. Rice and barley, truly, are the sacrificial essence of all animals (victims) 2; with that same essence he now completes that (victim) and makes it whole. This is why he subsequently prepares a sacrificial cake.  02 And why he proceeds with that cake after performing (offering) with the omentum is this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Now there are three elevens at the animal offering,&amp;ndash;eleven fore-offerings, eleven after-offerings, and eleven by-offerings: ten fingers, ten toes, ten vital airs, and the out-breathing, in-breathing and through-breathing&amp;ndash;this much constitutes man, who is the highest of animals, after whom 1 are all animals.  02 Now they say,&amp;rsquo; What, then, is done at the sacrifice whereby the vital air is kindly to all the limbs?&amp;rsquo;  03 When he divides the hind-part into three portions,&amp;ndash;the hind-part being (an opening of the) vital air, and that (animal) extending from thence forward, that vital air pervades it all through.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/08/5/</guid>
      <description>01  He makes the additional by-offerings:&amp;ndash;with &amp;lsquo;Go thou to the sacrifice 1, Hail!&amp;rsquo; The sacrifice is water, and seed is water: he thus casts seed.  02 &amp;lsquo;Go thou to Soma, Hail!&amp;rsquo; Soma is seed: he thus casts seed.  03 &amp;lsquo;Go thou to the heavenly ether, Hail!&amp;rsquo; The heavenly ether is water, and seed is water: he thus casts seed.  04 &amp;lsquo;Go thou to Agni Vaiśvānara, Hail!&amp;rsquo; Agni Vaiśvānara (&amp;lsquo;belonging to all men&amp;rsquo;) is this earth, and she is a safe resting-place: upon that safe resting-place he thus produces (creatures).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/03/09/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Now Prajāpati (the lord of creatures), having created living beings, felt himself as it were exhausted 1. The creatures turned away from him; the creatures 2 did not abide with him for his joy and food.  02 He thought within him, &amp;lsquo;I have exhausted  myself, and the object for which 3 I have created has not been accomplished: my creatures have turned away from me, the creatures have not abode with me for my joy and food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/1/</guid>
      <description>01  The Upāṁśu (graha), forsooth, is the out-breathing of the Sacrifice 1, the Upāṁśu-savana (press-stone) the through-breathing, and the Antaryāma (graha) the in-breathing.  02 Now as to why it is called Upāṁśu. There is a graha called Aṁśu 2, that is Prajāpati: his out-breathing is this (graha); and because it is his out-breathing, therefore it is called Upāṁśu.  03 This (graha) he draws without a strainer 3: whereby he puts the out-breathing into him as one tending away from him, and thus this forward-tending out-breathing of his streams forth from him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/2/</guid>
      <description>01  The Upāṁśu (graha), forsooth, is his out-breathing, the Upāṁśu-savana (stone) his through-breathing,  and the Antaryāma (graha) his in-breathing.
02 Now as to why it is called Antaryāma. That which is the out-breathing is also the in-breathing and the through-breathing. Now, in drawing the Upāṁśu (graha), he puts into him that out-breathing which tends away from him; and in drawing the  Antaryāma, he puts into him that in-breathing which tends towards him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The Aindra-vāyava (graha), forsooth, is his speech; and as such belonging to his self 1. Now Indra, when he had hurled the thunderbolt at Vr̥tra, thinking himself to be the weaker, and fearing lest he had not laid him low, hid himself. The gods also hid themselves away in the same place.  02 The gods then said, &amp;lsquo;Verily, we know not if Vr̥tra be slain or alive: come, let one of us find out, if Vr̥tra be slain or alive!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Mitra and Varuṇa, forsooth, are his intelligence and will; and as such belonging to his self: whenever he desires anything in his mind, as &amp;lsquo;Would that this were mine! I might do this!&amp;rsquo; that is intelligence; and whenever that is accomplished, that is will 1. Now intelligence indeed is Mitra, and will is  Varuṇa; and Mitra is the priesthood, and Varuṇa the nobility; and the priesthood is the conceiver, and the noble is the doer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/01/5/</guid>
      <description>01  The Āśvina graha 1, forsooth, is his organ of hearing; hence in drinking it he turns (the cup) all round 2, since with that ear of his he hears all round.&amp;ndash;Now when the Bhr̥gus, or the Aṅgiras, attained the heavenly world, Cyavana the Bhārgava, or Cyavana the Āṅgirasa, was left behind here (on earth) decrepit and ghostlike 3.  02 But Śaryāta, the Mānava, just then wandered about here with his tribe, and settled near by that same place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/1/</guid>
      <description>01  The Śukra and Manthin (grahas), forsooth, are his eyes. Now the Śukra, indeed, is he that burns yonder (the sun); and because it burns there 1, therefore it is (called) Śukra (&amp;lsquo;bright&amp;rsquo;). And the Manthin, indeed, is the moon.  02 He mixes it with (barley) meal: thus he makes it to be gruel (mantha), whence it is (called) Manthin. Now those two (sun and moon); forsooth, are the eyes of these creatures; for were those two not to rise, these (creatures) could not distinguish even their own hands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/2/</guid>
      <description>01  The Āgrayaṇa graha, forsooth, is his self (body, trunk), and as such it is his all; for this self is one&amp;rsquo;s all. Therefore he draws it by means of this (earth), for of her is the bowl 1, and with a bowl he draws this (libation); and this (earth) is all, as this  graha is all: hence he takes it by means of this (earth).
02 He draws it full; for the &amp;lsquo;full&amp;rsquo; means all, and this graha is all: therefore he draws it full.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/3/</guid>
      <description>01  That Ukthya (graha), forsooth, is his undefined breath (vital air) 1, and as such it is that self of his; for the undefined breath is the self; it is his  vital energy. Hence he draws it by means of this (earth), because of her is the bowl, and he draws it with a bowl;&amp;ndash;for undecaying and immortal is this (earth), and undecaying and immortal is the vital energy; therefore he draws it by means of this (earth or bowl).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/4/</guid>
      <description>01  That (opening of) vital air of his which is in front, that, forsooth, is the Vaiśvānara (graha); and that which is behind is the Dhruva. Formerly, indeed, both these grahas, the Dhruva and Vaiśvānara, were drawn; and even now one of them is still drawn, to wit, the Dhruva 1. And if he acquire a knowledge of that (Vaiśvānara graha) either from the Karakas, or from anywhere else, let him pour it into the sacrificer&amp;rsquo;s cup; but this (Dhruva graha he pours) into the Hotr̥&amp;rsquo;s cup 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/02/5/</guid>
      <description>01  Having drawn the cups of Soma, and gone out (of the cart-shed to the high altar) 1, he offers the oblation of drops 2. The reason why he offers the oblation of drops is this. Whatever drops of that (Soma) are spilt here, to them he now wishes a safe journey to the Āhavanīya, for the Āhavanīya is the resting-place of offerings: this is why he offers the oblation of drops.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Having drunk (Soma) 1 and said, &amp;lsquo;We are  invited together 2,&amp;rsquo; he (the Adhvaryu) rises. He takes a piece of the cake, and at the place where the Acḥāvāka, being seated, is now (about to) recite, he puts the piece of cake in his hand and says, &amp;lsquo;O Acḥāvāka, say what thou hast to say!&amp;rsquo; Now, the Acḥāvāka was excluded (from the Soma) 3.
02 Indra and Agni preserved him for the production of creatures, whence the Acḥāvāka priest belongs to Indra and Agni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/2/</guid>
      <description>01  Now truly when the Hotr̥ praises (recites the śastra 1), he sings, and to him thus singing the  Adhvaryu responds (prati-ā-gar), whence the name response (pratigara).
02 [The Hotr̥] calls upon that (Adhvaryu) seated (before him) with his face towards the east 2. For all  others except the Udgātr̥ perform their priestly duties while facing the east, and in this manner that priestly duty of his is performed towards the east.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/3/</guid>
      <description>01  He presses out (the Soma juice) with &amp;lsquo;Ihā̃! Ihā̃ 1!&amp;rsquo; (hither), whereby he draws Indra nigh; and  with &amp;lsquo;Br̥hat! Br̥hat!&amp;rsquo; (great), whereby he draws Indra 2 nigh.
02 The Śukra and Manthin grahas he draws first, for thereby the Soma feast comes to be supplied with pure Soma (śukra). Thereupon the Āgrayaṇa, for that (cup) is drawn at all (three) feasts. Then the Marutvatīya cup; then the Ukthya, for here also there are songs of praise (Uktha) 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, they slay the sacrifice, when they spread (perform) it:&amp;ndash;to wit, when they press out the king (Soma), they slay him; when they quiet the victim, they slay it; and with mortar and pestle, with the upper and nether millstone, they slay the havis offering.  02 When slain, that sacrifice was no longer vigorous. By means of dakshiṇās (gifts to the priests) the gods invigorated it: hence the name dakshiṇā, because thereby they invigorated (dakshay) it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/03/5/</guid>
      <description>01  Now there are three kinds of gods,&amp;ndash;the Vasus, the Rudras, and the Ādityas. Between them the press-feasts are divided: the morning pressing belongs to the Vasus, the midday pressing to the Rudras, and the third pressing to the Ādityas. But the morning pressing belonged to the Vasus exclusively, and the midday pressing to the Rudras exclusively, and the third pressing to the Ādityas conjointly (with others).  02 The Ādityas then said, &amp;lsquo;As that morning pressing belongs exclusively to the Vasus, and that midday pressing exclusively to the Rudras, so offer ye now to us a libation before the common (pressing).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Savitr̥, forsooth, is his 1 mind: therefore he draws the Sāvitra cup. And, forsooth, Savitr̥ is his breath (vital air);&amp;ndash;when he draws the Upāṁśu cup, then he puts into him that vital air in front; and when he draws the Sāvitra cup, then he puts into him that vital air behind: thus those two vital airs on both sides are beneficial (or, put into him), both that which is above and that which is below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/2/</guid>
      <description>01  He proceeds with (the offering of) Soma&amp;rsquo;s rice-pap; for Soma is the sacrificial food of the gods; and here now sacrificial food is prepared for Soma on his part; and thus Soma is not excluded therefrom. It is a rice-pap (caru), for rice-pap is food for the gods, since rice-pap is boiled rice, and boiled rice is clearly food: therefore it is a rice-pap.  02 Neither at the morning feast, nor at the midday feast does he offer it, for those two press-feasts, the morning feast and the midday feast, are the exclusive feasts of the gods; and Soma is sacred to the Fathers 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The metres, forsooth, are the (draught) cattle of the gods. Even as harnessed cattle here on earth  draw for men, so do the harnessed metres draw the sacrifice for the gods. And whenever the metres gratified the gods, then the gods gratified the metres. Now it has been previous to this, that the harnessed metres have drawn the sacrifice to the gods, that they have gratified them 1:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, it is nine Samishṭayajus 1 he offers on this occasion. The reason why he offers nine Samishṭayajus is that those stotra-verses at the Bahishpavamāna 2 chant amount to nine. Thus there is at both ends an inferior (incomplete) virāj 3, for the  sake of production: it was from that same inferior (lower) source of production on both sides that Prajāpati produced the creatures,&amp;ndash;from the one (he created) the upright, and from the other those tending to the ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/04/5/</guid>
      <description>01  He now betakes himself to the expiatory bath (avabhr̥tha). The reason why he betakes himself to the expiatory bath is this. What vital sap there has been in him (Soma and the sacrificer), that (sap) of his he (the priest) has produced (extracted) for the offerings. Now that body (of Soma, i.e.  the Soma-husks),&amp;ndash;there is no sap in it; (yet) it is not to be cast away: they take it down to the water and&amp;ndash;water being sap&amp;ndash;he puts that sap into it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/1/</guid>
      <description>01  He proceeds with the rice-pap to Aditi, as the concluding oblation. The reason why there is a rice-pap for Aditi is this. Because, on that former occasion 1, the gods said to her, &amp;lsquo;Thine forsooth shall be the opening, and thine the concluding oblation,&amp;rsquo; therefore he prepares that share for her at both ends (of the Soma-sacrifice).  02 And because, on that occasion, he offers when about to go forth (upa-pra-i) to buy the king (Soma), therefore that (opening oblation) is called Prāyaṇīya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/10/</guid>
      <description>01  If the Soma is carried off, let him say, &amp;lsquo;Run about and seek!&amp;rsquo; If they find it, why should they care? But if they do not find it, atonement is made therefore.  02 Now there are two kinds of Phālguna plants,  the red-flowering and the brown-flowering. Those Phālguna plants which have brown flowers one may press; for they, the brown-flowering Phālgunas, are akin to the Soma-plant: therefore he may press those with brown flowers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/2/</guid>
      <description>01  They lay hands on the barren cow 1, and having laid hands on it, they quiet it. It having been quieted 2, he says (to the slaughterer), &amp;lsquo;Pull out the omentum!&amp;rsquo; The omentum having been pulled out 2, let him tell (the slaughterer) to search groping for an embryo. If they do not find one, why need they care? and if they find one, atonement is made therefore.  02 For surely it is not right that, thinking it to be one (cow), they should perform, as it were, with that one; or that, thinking them to be two, they should perform, as it were, with two 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/3/</guid>
      <description>01  The Shodaśin 1 (graha) forsooth is Indra. Now, at one time the beings surpassed (ati-ric)  Indra&amp;ndash;the beings being the creatures&amp;ndash;they were in a state of equality, as it were, with him.
02 Indra then bethought himself, &amp;lsquo;How can I stand forth over everything here, and how may everything here be beneath me?&amp;rsquo; He saw that graha, and drew it for himself. Then he stood forth over everything here, and everything here was  beneath him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/5/</guid>
      <description>01  Prajāpati, forsooth, is that sacrifice which is performed here, and from which these creatures have been produced: and in like manner are they produced thereafter even to this day.  02 After the Upāṁśu cup goats are produced. Now that (cup) is again employed in the sacrifice: hence creatures are here produced again and again.  03 After the Antāryama cup sheep are produced. Now that (cup) is again employed at the sacrifice: hence creatures are here produced again and again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/6/</guid>
      <description>01  Prajāpati, forsooth, is that sacrifice which is here performed, and whence these creatures have been produced, and in like manner are they produced therefrom even to this day. Having drawn the Aśvina graha, he makes (the sacrificer) eye (the several cups, while muttering) the Avakāśa formulas 1.  02 The Upāṁśu cup he eyes first with (Vāj. S. VII, 27), &amp;lsquo;For mine out-breathing, (a) giver of lustre 2, become thou pure for lustre!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/7/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, there are here thirty-four utterances, called expiations 1. Prajāpati, forsooth, is that sacrifice which is performed here, and from which these creatures have been produced,&amp;ndash;and in like manner are they produced therefrom even to this day.  02 There are eight Vasus, eleven Rudras, twelve Ādityas; and these two, Heaven and Earth, are the (thirty-second and) thirty-third. And there are thirty-three gods, and Prajāpati is the thirty-fourth;&amp;ndash;thus he makes him (the sacrificer, or Yajña) to be Prajāpati 2: now that 3 is, for that is immortal, and what is immortal that is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/8/</guid>
      <description>01  Now when at that Trirātra 1 sacrifice he gives those thousand (cows), then that one is made the one-thousandth 2. On the first day he brings three hundred and thirty-three; and likewise on the second day he brings three hundred and thirty-three; and likewise on the third day he brings three hundred and thirty-three. Then that one-thousandth is left over.  02 She should be three-coloured, they say, for that is the most perfect form for her.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/05/9/</guid>
      <description>01  When he performs a twelve days’ sacrifice with transposed metres (Dvādaśāha vyūḍḥacḥandas), then he (the Adhvaryu) transposes the grahas (cups of Soma); and both the Udgātr̥ and the Hotr̥ transpose the metres. Now there is first that normal Tryaha (triduum), with settled metres 1: there he draws the cup beginning with the Aindravāyava.  02 Then, on the fourth day, he transposes the grahas, and they transpose the metres.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, the Aṁśu (graha), forsooth, is no other than Prajāpati: that (cup) is his (Yajña&amp;rsquo;s or the  Sacrificer&amp;rsquo;s) self 1, for Prajāpati is the self. Hence when they draw that (cup) they produce that self of his. Therein they lay these vital airs, according to as these vital airs, the grahas, are explained 2; and verily the sacrificer is born with his whole body in yonder world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/3/</guid>
      <description>01  Now as to the manner of animal offerings. One may perform with the (ordinary) set of eleven victims. He seizes one for Agni as the first victim, and one for Varuṇa (as the last); then again one for Agni.: in this way let him perform with the set of eleven victims 1.  02 Or one may day after day seize a victim for Indra and Agni; for all the gods are Agni, since in Agni offering is made to all the deities; and Indra is the deity of the sacrifice: thus he neither offends any of the deities, nor does he offend him who is the deity of the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/4/</guid>
      <description>01  Then as to the Mahāvratīya (graha) 1. Now when Prajāpati had created the living beings, his  joints were relaxed: with his relaxed joints he was unable to raise himself. Then the gods went on praising and toiling. They saw this Mahāvratīya (cup) and drew it for him: thereby they restored his joints.
02 With his joints thus restored, he approached this food, what food of Prajāpati there is,&amp;ndash;for what eating is to men, that the vrata (fast-food, or religious observance generally) is to the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/5/</guid>
      <description>01  Now the graha 1, forsooth, is he that burns yonder, since by him all these creatures are held (swayed). Hence they say, &amp;lsquo;We take (grab) the grahas,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;They walk, seized by the grahas.&amp;rsquo;  02 The graha, forsooth, is Vāc (speech); for by speech everything is swayed (grab) here 2,&amp;ndash;what wonder, then 3, that Vāc is the graha?  03 The graha, forsooth, is the name, for everything is held (fixed) by a name here,&amp;ndash;what wonder, then, that the name is the graha?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/6/</guid>
      <description>01  Now once on a time the gods, while performing sacrifice, were afraid of an attack from the Asura-Rakshas. They said, &amp;lsquo;Who of us shall sit on the south side; we will then enter upon the sacrifice on the north side in a place free from danger and injury.&amp;rsquo;  02 They said, &amp;lsquo;He who is the strongest of us, let him sit on the south side; we will then enter upon the sacrifice on the north side in a place free from danger and injury.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/7/</guid>
      <description>01  Threefold, forsooth, is science; the R̥cs, the Yajus, and the Sāmans. The R̥cs are this (earth), since it is thereon that he who sings them, does sing them; the R̥cs are speech, since it is by speech that he who sings them, does sing them. And the Yajus, forsooth, are the air, and the Sāmans the sky. That same threefold science is used in the Soma-sacrifice.  02 By the R̥c he conquers this world, by the Yajus the air, and by the Sāman the sky.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/8/</guid>
      <description>01  Now the consecration-ceremony 1 (for the sacrificial session) is a sitting down, is a session (sattra): hence they say of them, &amp;rsquo;they sit.&amp;rsquo; And when thereafter they perform the sacrifice, then they (under)go; then he, who is the leader, leads: hence they say of them, &amp;rsquo;they (under)go 2.&#39;  02 The consecration-ceremony, then, is a sitting down, it is a session, it is an (under)going, it is the (under)going of a session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNKNOWN_TITLE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/04/06/9/</guid>
      <description>01  Now, once on a time, the gods were sitting 1 in a sacrificial session, thinking, &amp;lsquo;May we attain excellence; may we be glorious, may we be eaters of food!&amp;rsquo; That same food, gained by them, wished to go away from them,&amp;ndash;and, food being cattle, it was the cattle that wished to go away from them, thinking, &amp;lsquo;It is to be feared lest they, being exhausted, may hurt us 2: how, indeed, will they deal with us?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>V. THE KÂTURMÂSYÂNI  SEASONAL SACRIFICES.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/02/05/1/</guid>
      <description>01  Verily, in the beginning, Prajāpati alone existed here 1. He thought within himself, &amp;lsquo;How can I be propagated?&amp;rsquo; He toiled and practised austerities. He created living beings 2. The living beings created by him passed away: they are those birds. Now man is the nearest to Prajāpati; and man is two-footed: hence birds are two-footed.  02 Prajāpati thought within himself, &amp;lsquo;Even as formerly I was alone, so also am I now alone.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
