<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;विषयविभागः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;विषयविभागः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Darśapūrṇamāsau</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/01_darshapUrNamAsau/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/01_darshapUrNamAsau/</guid>
      <description>NEW AND FULL-MOON-SACRIFICES
01.01 अथातो दर्शपूर्णमासौ व्याख्यास्यामः॥१॥
 Now we shall explain the new and full moon-sacrifices.  प्रातरग्निहोत्रं हुत्वान्यमाहवनीयं प्रणीयाग्नीनन्वादधाति॥२॥ 2. After having performed the morning Agnihotra, having brought forward another (fire to the place of) Ahavaniya (from the Garhapatya) (the Adhvaryu) adds fuel to the fires&amp;rsquo;. 14. in the manner mentioned in 4-7.
न गतश्रियो ऽन्यमग्निं प्रणयति॥३॥ 15. In the case of a (sacrificer who is) Gataśrī,&amp;rsquo; he does not bring forward another fire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 yājamānam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/02_yAjamAnam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/02_yAjamAnam/</guid>
      <description>THE DUTIES OF A SACRIFICER
04.01 याजमानं व्याख्यास्यामः॥१॥
 We shall explain the duties of a sacrificer. . 140  यजमानस्य ब्रह्मचर्य दक्षिणादानं द्रव्यप्रकल्पनं कामानां कामनम॥२१॥ 2. To observe celibacy, to give gifts, to arrange the things (necessary for sacrfice), to have desires (are) the duties of the sacrificer.
प्रत्यगाशिषो मन्त्राञ्जपत्यकरणानुपतिष्ठतेऽनुमन्त्रयते॥३॥ 3. He mutters formulae containing blessings for himself, and not referring to actions; he stands near praising (some objects when necessary); (or) addresses (some objects when necessary) with formulae.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Agnyādheyaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/03_agnyAdheyaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/03_agnyAdheyaH/</guid>
      <description>(AGNYĀDHEYA) ESTABLISHMENT OF THE FIRES
05.01 अग्न्याधेयं व्याख्यास्यामः॥१॥
 We shall explain Agnyādheya (establishment of the fires).V.1] ĀPŚS Translation : THITE 171   यो अश्वत्थः शमीगर्भ आरुरोह त्वे सचा। तं ते हरामि ब्रह्मणा यज्ञियैः केतुभिः सहेति शमीगर्भस्याश्वत्थस्यारणी आहरति॥२॥ 2. With yo asvatthaḥ&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo; the performer brings churning sticks out of the ASvattha-tree grown on a Sami-tree.2
 TB I.2.1.8-9 Cp. SB XI.5.1.13.  अप्यशमीगर्भस्येति वाजसनेयकम्॥३॥ 3. “Even out of the (ASvattha-tree) not grown on a Sami tree” —this is the vew of the Vajasaneyins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 PUNARĀDHĀNAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/04_punarAdhAnam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/04_punarAdhAnam/</guid>
      <description>PUNARĀDHĀNA (RE-ESTABLISHMENT OF FIRES)
05.26 पुनराधेयं व्याख्यास्यामः॥१॥
 We shall explain Punarādheya (re-establishment of fire).  तस्याग्न्याधेयवत्कल्पः॥२॥ 2. Its procedure is similar to that of Agnyādhāna. 220 [V.26 220 ApSs Translation : THITE
अग्नीनाधायैतस्मिन्संवत्सरे यो नर्गुयात्स पुनरादधीत प्रजाकामः पण पष्टिकामो ज्यान्यां पुत्रमायां स्वेष्वारुध्यमानेषु यदा वाड़ेन विधरतां नीया 3. He who will not prosper after having established fire in that year should establish them again. (Similarly) a sacri ficer desirous of progeny, desirous of cattle, desirous of proc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 agnihotram</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/05_agnihotram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/05_agnihotram/</guid>
      <description>AGNIHOTRA
06.01 अग्निहोत्रं व्याख्यास्यामः॥१॥
 We shall explain the Agnihotra.1 Libation of milk in fire in the evening and morning.  अधिवृक्षसूर्य आविःसूर्ये वा धृष्टिरसि ब्रह्म यच्छेत्युपवेषमादाय गार्हपत्यमभिमन्त्रयते सुगार्हपत्य इति॥२॥ 2. When (in the evening) the sun is at the top of the trees or when the sun is visible (in the morning), with dhrstirast brahma yacchal, having taken the poking stick (Upavesa) in his hand, with sugārhapatyah&amp;hellip;2 the Adhvaryu addresses the Gārhapatya(-fire).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 ĀGRAYANEṢTI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/06_AgrayaneShTiH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/06_AgrayaneShTiH/</guid>
      <description>ĀGRAYANEṢTI: (OFFERING OF NEW AGRICULTURAL PRODUCT) नानिष्ट्वाग्रयणेनाहितार्निवस्याश्नीयात्॥२॥ 2. A sacrificer who has established fires should not eat the new agricultural product without having performed the Agrayana-offering.&amp;rsquo; 1.Cf. KS XII.7.
वीहीणां यवानां श्यामाकानामित्यग्रपाकस्य यजेत॥३॥ 3. He should offer the new agricultural product viz. rice, barley, or Syāmāka (panicum frumentaceum).
अमावास्यायां पौर्णमास्यां वा॥४॥ 4. On the New or Full-moon-day.1
 Thus either before or after the New moon-sacrifice or full-moon sacrifice.  आमावास्यं तन्त्रम्॥५॥ 5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Paśubandhaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/07_pashubandhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/07_pashubandhaH/</guid>
      <description>PAŚUBANDHA (ANIMAL-SACRIFICE)
07.01 सर्वांल्लोकान्पशुबन्धयाग्यभिजयति॥१॥
 The performer of an animal-sacrifice&amp;rsquo; wins all the worlds. This animal-sacrifice is called Nirudhapasubandha (an animal sacrifice which has been &amp;ldquo;taken out” from the Soma-sacrifice). Animal-sacrifice is basically a part of a Soma-sacrifice. But here it is described as an independent rite.  तेन यक्ष्यमाणो ऽमावास्यायां पौर्णमास्यां वा षड्ढोतारं मनसानुगुत्याहवनीये सग्रहं जुहोति सूर्यं ते चक्षुरिति॥२॥ 2. (When) the (sacrificer) is going to perform it, having mentally recited the Ṣaddhotr-formula&amp;rsquo; on the New or Full moon day the Adhvaryu offers a libation of ghee in the Ahavaniya (fire) with the portion called graha (in the Saddhotr formula) viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 cāturmāsyam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/08_chAturmAsyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/08_chAturmAsyam/</guid>
      <description>THE CĀTURMĀSYA (FOUR-MONTHLY) SACRIFICES
1 Vaiśvadevaparva | A. THE VAIŚVADEVA-PARVAN
08.01 अक्षय्यं ह वै चातुर्मास्ययाजिनः सुकृतं भवति॥१॥
 Imperishable, indeed, is the merit of the performer of the Cāturmāsya (fourmonthly sacrifices).&amp;rsquo; ___1. Cp SB II.6.3.1. 353  फाल्गन्यां पौर्णमास्यां चैत्र्यां वा वैश्वदेवेन यजते॥२॥ 2. One should perform the Vaiśvadeva (part of the Cāturmāsya-sacrifices) on the full-moon-day of Phālguna or of Caitra.
पूर्वस्मिन्पर्वणि पञ्चहोतारं मनसानुद्रुत्याहवनीये सग्रहं हुत्वान्वारम्भणीया मिष्टिं निर्वपति वैश्वानरं द्वादशकपालं पार्जन्यं च चरुम्॥३॥ 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Prāyaścittayaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/09_prAyashchittayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/09_prAyashchittayaH/</guid>
      <description>THE EXPIATIONS
09.01 श्रुतिलक्षणं प्रायश्चित्तं विध्यपराधे विधीयते॥१॥
 An expiation characterised by (mentioned in) the Śruti (Veda) is prescribed in the case of a mistake in the performance.  एकस्मिन्दोषे श्रूयमाणानि प्रायश्चित्तानि समभ्युच्चीयेरन्नर्थान्तरत्वात्॥२॥ 2. The expiations being heard (in the Veda) in connection with one and the same defect should be combined together (i.e. only one (and not all) should be performed) because the purpose is different.&#39;
 A sacrificer who has omitted either of the new and full moon offerings should perform either an offering to Agni PathikȚt (15 II.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Agniṣṭomaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/10_agniShTomaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/10_agniShTomaH/</guid>
      <description>THE SOMA-SACRIFICE: AGNIṢṬOMA
10.01 सोमेन यक्ष्यमाणो ब्राह्मणानार्षेयानृत्विजो वृणीते यूनः स्थविरान्वानूचा नानूर्ध्ववाचोङ्गहीनान्॥१॥ ____1. One who is going to perform a Soma-sarifice should select priests who must be Brāhmaṇas belonging to Rṣi-families, 488 being either young or old, those who have studied Veda. I those who have loud voice and those who are not devoid of any limbi ___1. For this qualification cf SB III.1.1.5. तेभ्यः सोमं प्राह॥२॥ 2. He (the sacrificer) tells them (through Somapravāka) about the Soma(-sacrifice).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 agniṣṭoma-vikārāḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/11_agniShToma-vikArAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/11_agniShToma-vikArAH/</guid>
      <description>FURTHER TYPES OF SOMA-SACRIFICES
14.01 उक्थ्यः षोडश्यतिरात्रो ऽप्तोर्यामश्चाग्निष्टोमस्य गुणविकाराः॥१॥
 Ukthya, Sodasin, Atiratra, Aptoryāma are the modi fications of the Agniṣṭoma.  उक्थ्येन पशुकामो यजेत। षोडशिना वीर्यकामः। अतिरात्रेण प्रजाकामः पशुकामो वा। अप्तोर्यामेणातिरात्रेण सर्वान्कामानवाप्नोति॥२॥ 2. (A sacrificer) desirous of cattle should perform an Ukthya sacrifice; &amp;hellip;desirous of power a Sodasin, &amp;hellip;desirous of progeny or desirous of cattle Atirātra&amp;hellip;; (the sacrificer) obtains all the desired (things) by means of Aptoryāma-Atirātra.
 Cf. TS VI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 PAŚVEKĀDAŚINĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/12_pashvekAdashinI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/12_pashvekAdashinI/</guid>
      <description>776 PAŚVEKĀDAŚINĪ (ELEVEN-ANIMALS-SACRIFICE)
14.05 क्रतुपशव ऐकादशिनाश्च विकल्पन्ते॥१॥
 The animals which are normal to a sacrificel and those conneted with the eleven (number) are alternatives to each other. See XII.18.12-14. 2. Enumerated in TS V.5.22: a he-goat with black neck for Agni, a ewe for Sarasvati, a brown he-goat for Soma, a grey he-goat for Pūṣan, a he-goat with white back for BỊhaspati, a spotted he-goat for Viśvedevas, a reddish he-goat for Indra, a speckled he-goat for Maruts, a mixed-coloured he-goat for Indra and Agni, a he goat with black below for Savits and a wether for Varuṇa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 brahmā some</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/13_brahmA_some/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/13_brahmA_some/</guid>
      <description>XIV.8 THE BRAHMAN&amp;rsquo;S DUTIES IN A SOMA-SACRIFICE. वासिष्ठो ब्रह्मा ज्योतिष्टोमे॥१॥
 In the Jyotiṣtoma (-sacrifice) the Brahman (should be one) belonging to the Vasiṣtha (family).&#39; Cf. TS III.5.2.1.  यो वा कश्चित्स्तोमभागान्विद्यात्॥२॥ 2. Or any one who knows the Stomabhāga (-formulae).&#39;
 Cp. ṢaļB 1.5.3.  आध्वर्यवेषु कर्मसु स्तुतशस्त्रयोश्च वाचं यच्छति। अन्तधौं च॥३॥ 3. At the time of the works of the Adhvaryu and at the time of Stotras and Sastras, he restrains his speech; and also during the interval.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 dakṣiṇāḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/14_daxiNAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/14_daxiNAH/</guid>
      <description>14.11 THE DAKSINAS (SACRIFICIAL GIFTS) दक्षिणां प्रतिग्रहीष्यन्सप्तदशकृत्वो ऽपान्य व्यावृत्य प्रतिगृह्णीयात्॥१॥
 When about to accept the sacrificaial gift, having taken breath for seventeen times, (and) having turned away (from it) one should accept it.&#39; Cf. TB II.2.5.1; II.3.2.1. See also XIV.12.6.XIV.12] ÁpśS Translation : THITE 793  देवस्य त्वा सवितुः प्रसवे ऽश्विनोर्बाहुभ्यां पूष्णो हस्ताभ्यां प्रतिगृह्णामि। राजा त्वा वरुणो नयतु देवि दक्षिणे। अग्नये हिरण्यं तेनामृतत्वमश्याम्। वयो दात्रे मयो मह्यमस्तु प्रतिग्रही।। क इदं कस्मा अदात्। कामः कामाय। कामो दाता कामः प्रतिग्रहीता। कामं समुद्रमाविश कामेन त्वा प्रतिगृह्णामि। कामैतत्ते। एषा ते काम दक्षिणा उत्तानस्त्वाङ्गीरसः प्रतिगृह्णात्विति॥२॥ 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 cāturhotram</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/15_chAturhotram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/15_chAturhotram/</guid>
      <description>THE RITUAL OF THE CATURHOTR-FORMULAE
14.13 संवत्सरं चतुर्णामेको नाश्नीयात्। तद्वतमिति विज्ञायते चतुर्होतॄणामनुब्रुवा णस्य॥१॥
 In connection with one who is studying the Caturhotr. formulael it is known (from a Brāhmaṇa-text): “One should not eat for a year, being one of the four. This is the vow.&amp;quot;? TA III.2. MS I.9.6.  एषा वा अनाहिताग्नेरिष्टिर्यच्चतु)तारः॥२॥ 2. The (offering with the) Caturhotr-formulae indeed (forms) an offering for one who has not established the sacred fires.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 soma-prāyaścittayaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/16_soma-prAyashchittayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/16_soma-prAyashchittayaH/</guid>
      <description>EXPIATIONS FOR THE SOMA-SACRIFICES XIV.16 अग्निं नरो दीधितिभिररण्योर्हस्तच्युती जनयन्त प्रशस्तम्। दूरदृशं गृहपति- मथर्युम्॥ अग्निनाग्निः समिध्यते। सप्त ते अग्ने। मनो ज्योतिर्जुषताम्। त्रयस्त्रिंशत्॥ यन्मे मनसश्छिद्रं यद्वाचो यच्च मे हृदः। अयं देवो बृहस्पतिः सं तसिञ्चतु राधसा॥ विश्वकर्मा हविरिदं जुषाणः संतानैर्यज्ञं समिमं तनोतु। या व्युष्टा उषसो याश्च निम॒चस्ता संदधामि हविषा घृतेन॥ अयाश्चाग्ने ऽसि। त्वं नो अग्ने। स त्वं नो अग्ने॥ भद्रं कर्णेभिः शृणुयाम देवा भद्रं पश्येमाक्षभिर्यजत्राः। स्थिरैरङ्गैस्तुष्टुवांसस्तनूभिर्व्यशेम देवहितं यदायुः॥ स्वस्ति न इन्द्रो वृद्धश्रवाः स्वस्ति नः पूषा विश्ववेदाः। स्वस्ति नस्तायो अरिष्टनेमिः स्वस्ति नो बृहस्पतिर्दधातु॥ पृषदश्वा मरुतः पृश्निमातरः शुभंयावानो विदथेषु जग्मयः। अग्निजिह्वा मनवः सूरचक्षसो विश्वे नो देवा अवसा गमन्निह॥ शतमिन्नु शरदो अन्ति देवा यत्रा नश्चक्रा जरसं तनूनाम्। पुत्रासो यत्र पितरो भवन्ति मा नो मध्या रीरिषतायुर्गन्तोः॥ प्रेद्धो अग्ने दीदिहीत्येषा॥१॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 pravargyam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/17_pravargyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/17_pravargyam/</guid>
      <description>15.01 PRAVARGYA प्रग्वर्यं संभरिष्यन्नमावास्यायां पौर्णमास्यामापूर्यमाणपक्षस्य या पर नक्षत्रे तूष्णीं काण्टकी समिधमाधाय युञ्जते मन इति चतुर्गहीतं जुहोतिमा
 One who is going to collect (prepare the utensils required for) the Pravargya,on the new-moon-day or the full moon-day or under an auspicious constellation of the fortnight of the waxing (moon), having silently (without any formula) put a thorny fuel-stick (on the fire) offers four-times-scooped (ghee) (in the fire) with yuñjate mana uta yuñjate&amp;hellip;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 AGNICAYANAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/18_agnichayanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/18_agnichayanam/</guid>
      <description>AGNICAYANA (FIRE-ALATAR-BUILDING)
16.01 अग्निं चेष्यमाणो ऽमावास्यायां पौर्णमास्यामेकाष्टकायां वोखां संभरति॥१॥
 (The sacrificer) who is going to build fire (-altar) should collect (the material for) the Ukhā (fire-pan) either on the Newmoon day or Full-moon-day or on the Ekaṣṭaka-day.&#39; Cf. ŚB VI.2.2.23. Ekāstakā means the eighth day in the black fortnight in the month of Māgha. 898  अषाढामधिकृत्यैके समानन्ति॥२॥ 2. Some think that (this is to be done) on the Aṣādha.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 VĀJAPEYAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/19_vAjapeyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/19_vAjapeyam/</guid>
      <description>18.01 VĀJAPEYA शरदि वाजपेयेन यजेत ब्राह्मणो राजन्यो वर्द्धिकामः॥१॥
 A Brahmin or a Ksatriya who wants to get prosperity should perform the Vājapeya (-sacrifice) in autumn.  नित्यवदेके समामनन्ति॥२॥ 2. Some think (it) to be obligatory as it were.
प्रजापतिमाप्नोति॥३॥ 3. He thereby obtains Prajāpati.&#39;
 Cf. TMB XVIII.7.5.  तस्य षोडशिवत्कल्पः॥४॥ 4. Its procedure is like that of the Sodasin. ____1. See XIV.2.2-3.7.
सर्वः सप्तदशो भवति॥५॥ 5. It consists of seventeen everywhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 RĀJASŪYAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/20_rAjasUyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/20_rAjasUyam/</guid>
      <description>18.08 RAJASŪYA राजा स्वर्गकामो राजसूयेन यजेत॥१॥
 A king desirous of heaven should perform the Rājasūya sacrifice.  शतसहस्रं दक्षिणा॥२॥ 2. One hudred thousand (cows) are the sacrificial gift (dakṣiṇā).
अग्निष्टोमः पञ्चापवर्गः प्रथममहः॥३॥ 3. An Agniṣtoma ending after five days (is to be Performed) as the first day.
 Thus the Agniṣtoma is a one day sacrifice but before the Soma sacrificial day there is one dīkṣā day and three Upasad day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Sautrāmaṇi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/21_sautrAmaNi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/21_sautrAmaNi/</guid>
      <description>Caraka-Sautrāmaṇi SAUTRĀMAŅI: CARAKA-SAUTRĀMANĪ
19.01 यहे परस्तात्सीसेन क्लीबाच्छष्पाणि क्रीत्वा क्षौमे वासस्युपना निधाय सौत्रामण्यास्तन्त्रं प्रक्रमयति॥१॥
 Having purchased three days earlier (to the proper performance of the Sautrāmaṇī), the shoots (of Barley), from a euhuch with lead, then having kept and tied them in a cloth (the Adhvaryu) starts the procedure of the Sautrāmani. Cf. TB I.8.5.3.  तस्या निरूढपशुबन्धवत्कल्पः॥२॥ 2. The performance of it is similar to (that of) Nirudha paśubandha (an animal-sacrifice independent of the Soma sacrifice).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 cayana-kramāḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/22_chayana-kramAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/22_chayana-kramAH/</guid>
      <description>FIRE-ALTAR-BUILDING-RITUAL ACCORDING TO KATHA-SCHOOL SĀVITRA-FIRE-ALTAR-BUILDING
19.11 सावित्रं स्वर्गकामश्चिन्वीत॥१॥
 (The sacrificer) desirous of obtaining heaven&amp;rsquo; should build (the fire-altar) of the size of sun(with bricks). As was done by Ahīnas Āśvatthya . He built the altar of the shape of golden eagle in order to go the heaven (See TB III. 10.9.10-11). 1124 Translation : THITE [XIX.11  पशुबन्धे चीयते॥२॥ 2. (This type of altar) is built at the time of an animal sacrificel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Kāmya-paśavaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/23_kAmya-pashavaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/23_kAmya-pashavaH/</guid>
      <description>OPTIONAL ANIMAL-SACRIFICES
19.16 काम्यैः पशुभिरमावास्यायां पौर्णमास्यां वा यजेत॥१॥
 One should perform optional sacrifices with animals on a new-moon or full-moon day.1 Cp. VII.1.2.  तेषां निरूढपशुबन्धवकल्पः॥२॥ 2. The ritual of them is similar to that of the Nirudhapasu bandha.1
 For this see VII.1.1-28.8.  वायव्यं श्वेतमिति ते ब्राह्मणव्याख्याताः॥३॥ 3. The optional animal-sacrifices are described in the Brahmana-text beginning with vayavyam svetam&amp;hellip;1 __1. TS II.1.1.1-10.3.
तेषामावापिकेषु स्थानेषु यथादेवतं षड़चो निदधाति। वपायाः पुरोडाशस्य हविष इति द्वद्वे॥४॥ ____4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Kāmyāḥ iṣṭayaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/24_kAmyAH_iShTayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/24_kAmyAH_iShTayaH/</guid>
      <description>OPTIONAL (HAVIS-) OFFERINGS .
19.18 काम्याभिरिष्टिभिरमावास्यायां पौर्णमास्यां वा यजेत॥१॥
 One should perform the optional (Havis-) offerings on the New or Full moon day. 1151 ApSs Translation : THITE XIX.18] 151  ता ब्राह्मणव्याख्याताः॥२॥ 2. They are described by the Brāhmaṇa-text.&amp;rsquo; ___1. TS II.2.1-4.14.5.
समिध्यमानवती समिद्धवतीं चान्तरेण पृथुपाजवत्यौ धाय्ये दधाति। यथादिष्टं वानुपदावाज्यभागौ॥३॥ 3a. Between the two enkindling verses containing the word samidhyamāna and samiddha, respectively (the Hotr) puts (i.e. recites ) the two additional verses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Aśvamedhaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/25_ashvamedhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/25_ashvamedhaH/</guid>
      <description>ASVAMEDHA (HORSE-SACRIFICE)
20.01 राजा सार्वभौमो ऽश्वमेधेन यजेत। अप्यसार्वभौमः॥१॥
 A king, (who is) the lord of all the earth should perform the Aśvamedha (sacrifice) or even one who is not the lord of all the earth. 1177  चित्रा नक्षत्रम्॥२॥ 2. The constellation (on which the performance of sacrifice should begin, should be) Citra.
 The word Punyanāma in the Sūtra-text edited by Garbe should be a part of the next Sutra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Puruṣamedhaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/26_puruShamedhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/26_puruShamedhaH/</guid>
      <description>PURUSAMEDHA (MAN-SACRIFICE)
20.24 पञ्चाहः पुरुषमेधः॥१॥
 Purusamedha (Man-sacrifice) is a five-day (Soma sacrifice).  ब्राह्मणो राजन्यो वा यजेत॥२॥ 2. A Brahmin or a Kṣatriya may perform(it).
ओजो वीर्यमाप्नोति। सर्वा व्युष्टीय॑श्नुते॥३॥ 3. He obtains strength and power; obtains all the obtain ments.
एकादशसु यूपेप्वेकादशाग्नीपोमीयाः।।४॥ 4. There should be eleven (he- goats) to be offered to I४॥ 1230 Agni-Soma, (to be bound) at eleven sacrificial posts (on the day preceding the Soma days).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Sarvamedhaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/27_sarvamedhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/27_sarvamedhaH/</guid>
      <description>SARAVAMEDIIA (ALL-SACRIFICE) सर्वमेधो दशरात्रः॥३॥ 3. The Sarvamedha is a ten-day-(Soma-sacrifice).
राजा यजेत यः कामयेत सर्वमिदं भवेयमिति।४॥ 4. A king who desires, “May I be all this” should per form (it).
एकशतविधो ऽग्निः॥५॥ 5. The fire-altar-building should be hundred-fold.
अग्निष्टुदग्निष्टोमः प्रथममहः। सर्वमाग्नेयं भवति॥६॥ 6. The first day should be Agistut-Agnistoma (on it) eve rything (viz. the scoops, the Sastras and the Stotras) should be connected with Agni. _____ 1. For this sce XXII.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 Dvadaśāhaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/28_dvadashAhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/28_dvadashAhaH/</guid>
      <description>DVĀDAŚĀHA (TWELVE-DAY-SACRIFICE)
21.01 द्वादशाहेन प्रैव जायते ऽभि स्वर्ग लोकं जयत्येषु लोकेषु प्रतितिष्ठति॥१॥
 One produces progeny, one wins the heaven, one es tablishes in these worlds by means of Dvādaśāha sacrifice. _1. See TS VII.2.9.1.  साग्निचित्यो भवति॥२॥ 2. This (sacrifice) is accompanied with a fire-altar-build ing-rite.
सत्त्रमहीनश्च॥३॥ 3. (It can be) a Sattra and an Ahīna (type of sacrifice).
दीक्षितमदीक्षिता याजयेयुरहीने। एत एवत्विजो यजमानश्च सत्ते॥४॥ 4. In the Ahīna (type), the non-consecrated (priests) cause a consecrated (sacrificer) perform (the ritual).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Gavāmayanam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/29_gavAmayanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/29_gavAmayanam/</guid>
      <description>GAVĀMAYANA (-YEAR-LONG-SACRIFICIAL-SESSION)
21.15 गवामयनेन प्रजां भूतिं भूमानं गच्छन्त्यभि स्वर्ग लोकं जयन्त्येषु लोकेषु प्रतितिष्ठन्ति॥१॥
 By means of Gavāmayana the performers reach (ob tain) progeny, prosperity and amplitude; win the heaven; (and) become established in these worlds.  तस्य द्वादशाहेन सत्तभूतेन कल्पो व्याख्यातः॥२॥ 2. The ritual of it is explained by the Dvādaśāha performed as a Sattra (sacrificial session).
सप्तदशैके दीक्षाः समामनन्ति॥३॥ 3. According to some there should be seventeen Dikşā (-days).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Ekāhaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/30_ekAhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/30_ekAhaH/</guid>
      <description>ONE-DAY-SOMA-SACRIFICES: EKĀHA-S
22.01 एकाहेष्वहीनेष्विति प्राकृतीदक्षिणा ददाति। यथासमाम्नातं वा॥१॥
 In the one-day-sacrifices and Ahīnas (having two to twelve-soma-sacrificial days) (the sacrificer) should give the same gifts (as are to be given) in the basic paradigmatic Soma sacrifice or as has been mentioned in the sacred texts.&#39; e.g. XXII.4.24.  सर्वक्रतूमा प्रकृतिरग्निष्टोमः। निकायिनां तु प्रथमः सर्वत्र। यथादिष्टं AT11P11 2. The basic paradigm for all the sacrifices is Agniṣṭoma; that for the (sacrifices which) form group (and are mentioned under one name)&amp;rsquo; the first (one is the basic paradigm); or as has been mentioned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 Ahīnaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/31_ahInaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/31_ahInaH/</guid>
      <description>THE AHĪNA-SACRIFICES .XXII.14 द्विरात्रप्रभृतय उपरिष्टादतिरात्रा अहीना ऐकादशरात्रात्॥१॥
 The sacrifices beginning from two-day-sacrifices upto eleven-day-sacrifices, the last day of which is an Atirātra are called Ahīna.  तेषां द्वादशाहेनाहीनभूतेन कल्पो व्याख्यातः॥२॥ 2. The procedure of them is as good as explained by the twelve-day-soma-sacrifice performed as an Ahīna.&#39;
 The Dvadaśāha can be performed as an Ahīna or a Sattra. See XXI.1.3-4. 1335  दिरावस्यैन्द्रवायवाग्रं प्रथममहः शुक्राग्रमुत्तरम्॥३॥ 3. In the two-day-Ahīna sacrifice on the first day the Aindravāyava scoop is drawn first; on the second day the scoop for śukra (is drawn) first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>32 savāḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/32_savAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/32_savAH/</guid>
      <description>THE SAVAYAJÑAS
22.25 अथ सवानां व्याख्यातो बृहस्पतिसवः॥१॥
 Now the description of the Savas. The Bṣhaspatisava has been explained. The Savayajñas are generally one-day-sacrifices consisting of sprinkling of water etc. (Abhişeka) on the sacrificer.  वैश्यः पुष्टिकामः॥२॥ 2. A Vaiśya-sacrificer desirous of prosperity&amp;rsquo; (should per form the Vaiśyasava).&amp;rsquo; . 1. Cp. TB 11.7.2.1.
आग्नेयादीनि सप्त हवींषि निर्वपति॥३॥ 3. (The Adhvaryu) performs the seven offerings beginning with the one to Agni.!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>33 sattrāṇi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/33_sattrANi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/33_sattrANi/</guid>
      <description>THE SATTRA (SACRIFICIAL SESSIONS)
23.01 चतुर्विंशतिपरमाः सत्त्रमासीरन्॥१॥
 At the most twenty-four (persones) may perform a sacrificial session.  तेषां द्वादशाहेन सत्तभूतेन कल्पो व्याख्यातो यानि पुरस्तात्संवत्सरात्। गवामयनेनेतरेषाम्॥२॥ 2. The procedure of those sessions which (come to an end) before a year, has been explained by (the explanation of the Dvādaśāha of Sattra-type&amp;rsquo;; of others by the Gavāmayana.2
 See XXI.1.1-14.15. See XXI.15.1-23.14.  उभयतोऽतिरात्राणि भवन्ति॥३॥ 3. (The sacrificial sessions) are (those) on the both-sided, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>34 Paribhāṣāḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/34_paribhAShAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/34_paribhAShAH/</guid>
      <description>THE PARIBHĀSĀ-S OR THE GENERAL RULES.
24.01 यज्ञं व्याख्यास्यामः॥१॥
 We shall explain sacrifice.  स त्रयाणां वर्णानां ब्राह्मणराजन्ययोर्वैश्यस्य च॥२॥ 2. It is meant for three classes Brāhmana, Ksatriya, and Vaiśya.
स त्रिभिदैविधीयते॥३॥ 3. It is performed with the help of three Vedas.
ऋग्वेदयजुर्वेदसामवेदैः॥४॥ 4. (It is performed) with the help of the R̥gveda, Yajurveda, Samaveda.
ऋग्वेदयजुर्वेदाभ्यां दर्शपूर्णमासौ॥५॥ 5. The New and Full-moon-sacrifices are performed with the help R̥gveda and Yajurveda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>35 pravarāḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/35_pravarAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/35_pravarAH/</guid>
      <description>THE PRAVARAS (SERIES OF ANCESTORS)
24.05 प्रवरान्व्यास्यामः॥१॥
 We shall explain the series of ancestors.  आर्षेयं वृणीते। बन्धोरेव नैत्यथो संतत्या इति विज्ञायते॥२॥ 2. “One mentions the Rṣi-ancestors in the Pravara. Thus one does not go away form the connection; it is done for the sake of continuity&amp;quot;-thus is known (from a Brahmana-text).1
 TS II.5.8.7.  न देवैर्न मनुष्यैरायं वृणीते॥ ऋषिभिरेवार्षेयं वृणीत इति विज्ञायते॥३॥ 3. “He does not mention either gods or human beings in the Pravara of the Rṣis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>36 hautrakam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/36_hautrakam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/viShaya-vibhAgaH/36_hautrakam/</guid>
      <description>THE ACTIVITIES OF HOTR̥ IN AN IṢȚI (OFFERING)
24.11 . पुरस्तात्सामिधेनीनां होता हृदयदेश ऊर्ध्वं प्रादेशं धारयमाणो जपति मयि गृह्णाम्यग्रे अग्निं यो नो अग्निः पितर इति॥१॥
 Before (the ritual of) the Samidheni (enkindling-vesses, 1445 the Hotr, while holding his hand stretched up near the place of the heart, should mutter muyi grhņāmi&amp;hellip;. (TS V.7.9a,b). i.e. after he has been ordered by the Adhvaryu to recite the Sāmidheni-verses (see II.12.1).  अन्तराहवनीयमुत्कर च प्रतीचीनं गच्छञपति कं प्रपद्ये तं प्रपद्ये। यत्ते प्रजापते शरणं छन्दस्तत्प्रपद्ये। यावत्ते विष्णो वेद तावत्ते करिष्यामि। नगो अग्नय उपद्रष्ट्रे नमो वायव उपश्रोत्रे नम आदित्यायानुख्यात्रे। जुष्टामत्र देवेभ्यो वाचमुद्यासं स्वधावती पितृभ्यः शुश्रूषेण्यां मनुष्येभ्यः। प्रशास्त आत्मना प्रजया पशुभिः प्रजापतिं प्रपद्ये। अभयं मे अस्तु। प्रजापत्यमनुवक्ष्यामि। वागाविज्यं करोतु मन आर्विज्यं करोतु। वाचं प्रपद्ये भूर्भुवः सुवरिति॥ सत्यं प्रपद्य इति वा॥२॥ 2.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
